<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most pleasaunt and delectable historie of Lazarillo de Tormes, a Spanyard and of his maruellous fortunes and aduersities. The second part. Translated out of Spanish and into English, by W.P.</title>
            <title>Lazarillo de Tormes. Part 2. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845010</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845010</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9880</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 405:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most pleasaunt and delectable historie of Lazarillo de Tormes, a Spanyard and of his maruellous fortunes and aduersities. The second part. Translated out of Spanish and into English, by W.P.</title>
                  <title>Lazarillo de Tormes. Part 2. English.</title>
                  <author>Phiston, William, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>W. P., fl. 1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T[homas] C[reede] for Iohn Oxenbridge, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Parrot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.P. = William Phiston?.</note>
                  <note>A continuation of "Lazarillo de Tormes" by Diego Hurtado de Mendoza. A different work from the "La segunda parte de La vida de Lazarillo de Tormes" by Juan de Luna.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Lazarillo de Tormes, the Spanyardes life.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MOST PLEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and delectable Hiſtorie of Lazarillo de Tormes, a Spanyard: AND OF HIS MARVELLOVS Fortunes and Aduerſities.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Spanish into English,</hi> By W. P.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>LABORE ET CONSTANTIA </head>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by T. C. for <hi>Iohn Oxenbridge,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Parrot. 159<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9880:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9880:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my verie good friend, Maiſter <hi>Ionas Tirill</hi> of <hi>Burstow,</hi> all <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe bee wished.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough good will and perfect friendſhip is not to be requited nor ſought with mony, yet ſuch is the exellencie thereof, that it is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times requited with ſome ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, wherwith the vertue is much more beautified, as it was with the good and wiſe King <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> of <hi>Spaine:</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen to vnderſtand, that one vnto whome hee had done great good by preferring him to honour, beſides many liberal gifts, was verie vnthankfull for the ſame; he anſwered in a milde maner, that a great good turne is neuer requited without ſome ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, euen ſo I may compare you in this happineſſe vnto him, and in vnhappineſſe my ſelfe vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: who for much good, haue returned but ill; wherefore I am the bolder, being acquainted ſo wel with your good diſpoſition, to ſhew my ſelf thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, being well aſſured that you cannot think of my ſeruice euill, ſeeing, (as I haue ſaide) you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies done well, beeing deliuered vnto mee by a
<pb facs="tcp:9880:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Gentleman of mine acquaintaunce, a ſmall Spaniſh Pamphlet, by him new done into Engliſh, intituled <hi>Lazarillo de Tormes,</hi> a Spanyard, diſcourſing the many hard fortunes &amp; aduerſities he ſuſteined in the Sea, beeing tranſformed into a Tuni Fiſh; though but a toy, yet I aſſure you paſsing pleaſaunt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable; which I haue aduentured to dedicate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: Onely crauing you will accept it as friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I preſent it willingly, and then I haue my one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requeſt. And ſo reſting in hope of your fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptance, I commit you to the Almightie, and this poore <hi>Lazarillo,</hi> to the friendly Readers cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend who wisheth you all hearts eaſe. <hi>I. O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9880:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Howe Lazarillo de Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, at the importunate requeſts of his frends, Imbarked himſelfe, to goe in the Voyage with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> made vnto <hi>Argel, and what happened vnto him in the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our worſhippe muſt vnderſtand, that the vnfortunate <hi>Lazaro de Tormes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this pleaſant life, exerciſing his office, and getting his meat and drink, (for that God made no ſuch office, and whiche is muche better then the beſt foure and twentie other offices in <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo,</hi>) and withall, both I and my wife being well paide, and contented with our new daughter, daily increaſing our houſholde ſtuffe, I for my part being well vſed, and hauing two ſutes of apparell, one for euerie day, and the other for the holy dayes, and my wife as much, with <hi>24.</hi> Roialls of Plate in my purſe, I came vnto this Towne, whither I ſhould not haue come, where at my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riual, I vnderſtood the newes (as other men do) of the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age vnto <hi>Argel.</hi> Whereunto diuers of my neighbors began to hearken, ſaying one to the other, let vs goe thither, for by that voyage wee may come home laden with golde and ſiluer: ſo that they began to put me into ſuch a couetous humor, that I imparted the ſame vnto my wife, wherunto ſhe, being deſirous to returne backe againe vnto the prieſt, anſwered me ſaying, do as you thinke good, but if you goe, and that it pleaſeth God to ſende you good fortune, I pray
<pb facs="tcp:9880:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you bring me a <hi>Moore</hi> for my ſlaue, to ſerue me all my life, and it ſhal ſuffice me, as alſo I pray you remember to bring ſome what to marry this your litle daughter, wherunto the <hi>Barbery</hi> Ducates, wherewith (they ſay) thoſe Dogges the <hi>Moores</hi> are ſo well ſtored will not bee amiſſe. With the which anſwere, togither with the couetous deſire I had, I determined (which I ſhould not haue done,) to goe on this voyage: From the which my maiſter the Prieſt diſſwaded me verie much, but I would not beleeue him. To conclude, I hauing many miſeries more to paſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in former times I had paſſed, I agreed with a Knight of the order of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> with whome I was well acquainted, to beare him company, and to ſerue him in the voyage, and that he ſhould beare my charges, with ſuch condition, that whatſoeuer I could get it ſhould be for my ſelfe. And ſo there were diuers that got, but it was vnto me a great and an vnfortunate mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, which although diuers men felt, yet I dare aſſure you I had ſufficient for my part. This Knight and I (with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others departed out of this Towne, in great Iollitie and much brauery, as in all voyages is commonly ſéene, but to auoyde tediouſneſſe, I will make no rehearſall of that which happened vnto vs in our iourny by land, for that it is nothing vnto the purpoſe, but we were no ſonner imbarked at <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in a good ſhip full of men, and victualls ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and in company of other ſhippes, but there aroſe in the ſea the moſte horrible and cruelleſt tempeſt that euer your worſhip heard of, whereby there happened the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt wracke and deſtruction of men, that had bene ſeene or knowne vpon the ſeas long time before: and in this ſtorme the worſt was, that the waues of the ſea did vs not ſo much harme, as our owne ſhippes did, one vnto the other, becauſe the tempeſt being by night, and the cruell waues riſing ſo high, and ſo big, there was not any of vs, that could ſée to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe any remedie for our ſafetie, but that whether we wold or not, the ſhippes ſtrake one againſt the other, in ſuch ſort, that with the blowes they forcibly brake and drowned in
<pb facs="tcp:9880:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ſea, with all the paſſengers. But for that your worſhip hath (as I ſaide) bene enformed at large of that which was happened in that tempeſt, by ſuch as beheld it and were in the ſame, and (as God woulde eſcaped,) as alſo by others that haue heard the ſame deliuered from their mouthes, it ſhall bee néedleſſe for me to touche any pointe thereof, more then of that whereof I my ſelfe am able to enforme you, as being onely he that ſawe it, and (which of all the reſt that were with vs,) ſawe it beſt: Wherein God ſhewed his great mercie vnto me, as your worſhip ſhall heare by the ſequell.</p>
               <p>I ſpeake neither of he <hi>Moore,</hi> nor yet of the <hi>Moore,</hi> for the diuell take them all for any that euer I ſawe, in that voyage: but I beheld our ſhippe broken in many péeces, I ſawe the like done by others, I perceiued neither maſt nor yarde in her, all the deckes broken vp, and the vpper part cleane carried away, at which ſight the Captaines and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers men of qualitie entered into the boate, ſéeking to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe themſelues in other ſhippes, although at that time there were verie fewe among vs that coulde helpe them; and left the meane and baſer ſort of vs within the ſhip, for that the common ſaying is, It is better to léeſe the worſt then the beſt. We ſéeing that, committed our ſoules vnto God, and began to confeſſe our ſelues one vnto the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the two Clarkes that were in our ſhip, naming them ſelues (as they ſay) ſouldiers of Ieſus Chriſt, went with the Captaines, and left vs as baſe companions vnto the mercie of the ſeas. But I for my part neuer heard ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull a confeſſion, as the poore men made being readie to die, and I am aſſured that there was not one among vs at that preſent that was not halfe dead, and diuers, which at euery waue of the ſea that entered into the broken ſhip, felt in a maner preſent death, in ſuch ſort as it might be ſayd (if it were poſſible) that they were one hundreth tunnes, and to ſay the truth, their confeſſions were of bodies in a maner without ſoules. Among diuers of them which I confeſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there were ſome that vttered not one worde out of their mouthes, but only ſighes, and ſobbes, (a thing common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men troubled and in aduerſitie,) and as much did I vnto them: In the ende we being in a manner drowned in our weake ſhippe, and wholly out of all hope of any remedie or aide to be looked for, I began to lament my death, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent me of my ſinnes, (but much more of my comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) and hauing recited certaine deuout Orazons, which I learned in my youth of my firſt maiſter, fit to be ſaid at ſuch a time, with the feare and horror of death I fell into a moſt horrible and deadly thirſt, and conſidering with my ſelfe that it would ſoone be quenched with the ſalt and vnſauory water of the ſea, it ſéemed vnto me a point of great inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to vſe ſmall charitie vnto my ſelfe, wherewith I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that it were good for me before that euill water entered into my bodie, to fill it firſt with moſt excellent wine, whereof at that preſent there was great ſtore in the ſhip: which at that time was as well without a maiſter, as I without a ſoule, ſo that with great deſire and much more haſte, I beganne to drinke, and with the great thirſt and the feare of death wherwith I was oppreſſed, togither with the extremitie thereof, (withall, I being no ſcholler but rather a maiſter in that Art,) and the great folly I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at that preſent, becauſe I perceiued not any one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to beare me company, I ſtood to my tackling ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, and drunke in ſuch maner, and ſo much, ſometimes reſting my ſelfe, and then beginning againe, that from the head to the foote, I felt not any part of my ſorrowfull bodie, but was all filled with wine, which I had no ſooner done, but the ſhip brake in péeces, and we all drowned in the ſea, as for my part, I was nothing elſe but wine: when the ſhip ſuncke it was about two houres after day appearing, at which ſight, by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wine that wrought in my head, féeling my ſelfe wholly vnder the water, and perceiuing not any meanes of helpe, nor knowing what to do, I laide hand on my ſword, which then I had at my ſide, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:9880:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I began to ſinke downeward into the ſea. At which time I might perceiue great quantitie of fiſhes both great and little, and of diuers kindes to draw nere vnto vs, and verie nimbly with their téeth aſſaild my dead companions, ſoone tearing and renting their bodies in péeces: which I beholding, was in great feare they would doo the like to me, if I ſhould ſtand vpon termes with them. Wherwith I left ſhaking of mine armes, as thoſe which were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſinking did, thinking thereby to eſcape death: but for I could not by anie meanes ſwim, I ſanke downwards into the Sea, and ſo laboured my heauie bodie, that I out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went that wicked companie and great multitude of fiſhes that (at the cracke which the ſhip gaue in breaking) came thither. And in this manner I deſcending downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward into the déepe ſea, I perceiued comming behinde mee a great and mightie Armie of other Fiſhes, and (as I thinke) they came with great deſire to learne ſome newes of me, and with great haſt approched nere me, that with their teeth they might teare me in peeces, and ſo eate me vp: but I perceiuing my ſelfe ſo compaſſed about with death, with the rage and feare whereof, not knowing how to eſcape, I began to ſkirmiſh and flouriſh about me with my ſword, which I held naked in my right hand, for that as yet I had not let it fall, and I plaid my part therewith ſo well, that in ſhort ſpace I made ſuch a riddance of them, laying about me both on the right ſide &amp; the left, that in the end they concluded among themſelues to recule backe, and for a time to leaue me in peace: and letting me reſt, began to buſie themſelues about the dead bodies of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that I in defending of my ſelfe had ſlaine, (which they preſently eate vp and deuoured): and ſurely I did it with little labour, by reaſon thoſe Fiſhes hauing ſmall meanes of defence, and their armes much weaker, it laye in me to kill and deſtroy as manie of them as I would. In the ende, a good ſpace after I had left them, deſcending and ſinking ſtill into the ſea, and that ſo ſtraight and directly
<pb facs="tcp:9880:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
downward, as if my féete beeing fixed vpon ſome certayne thing, my bodie had ſtood vpright. In the ende I chanced vpon a great rocke, which ſtood in the middeſt of the déepe ſea: and as I felt my féete vpon the ſame, I ſtayd my ſelfe for a time, and began to reſt after my great trouble and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſuſtained: which vntill then, by reaſon of the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that I found in my ſelfe, and feare of death withall, I had no time to thinke vppon. And as it is a common thing vnto all thoſe which are afflicted and wearyed to ſigh, being readie to fetch a great ſigh, which coſt me full deare: negligently opening my mouth, (which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I ſhut preſently againe) the wine hauing by that meanes gotten ſome vent, it being at the leaſt more than thrée houres after I drunke the ſame, at the iſſuing foorth made place for the ſalt and vnſauerie Water of the Sea, which as then entred into me, cauſing great paine and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my bodie, ſtriuing with her contrarie as then within me. Then I perceiued and ſaw the wine was the onely meanes that my life had ſo long béen preſerued in the ſea, by reaſon that my bodie euen to the verie throate being filled with the ſame, the Water of the Sea had no power nor place to enter in. And then likewiſe I knew the Prophecie to bee true that my maſter tolde me of tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſame, ſaying vnto me in <hi>Eſcalona,</hi> that if Wine could euer preſerue the life of man, it ſhould ſurely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue mine. Then it gréeued me to thinke vpon my dead companions in the ſea, becauſe they bare me not companie in drinking: which if they had done, they ſurely had béen liuing as well as I, and their companie would haue mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred ſome comfort vnto me. I did likewiſe in my ſelfe lament the miſerable caſe of all ſuch as then were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with vs, and began to thinke with my ſelfe, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture although they had dronke as I did, they would not all haue béen ſo wilfull and obſtinate as my ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not all <hi>Lazaroes de Tormes,</hi> who learned the Arte at that notable ſchoole of the Tauernes and Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb facs="tcp:9880:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of <hi>Toleda,</hi> in the companie of my maſters the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. In this manner calling to memorie theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other things, I perceiued a great quantitie of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes to approach vnto the place where I was, ſome riſing from the bottome of the Sea, others deſcending down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and all of them ioyning together, beſieged mee round about where I ſate. I ſaw and knew verie well that they came with an euill intent and meaning: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, hauing more feare than will, I began to riſe, and with much paine ſtood vppon my féete, thinking to defend my ſelfe againſt them: but all in vaine, being at that inſtant in a manner ſpoyled and ſtiffe with colde, by meanes of the euill water which had entered into my bodie, whereof I was ſo ſicke, that I could not by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie meanes ſuſtaine my ſelfe, nor yet once lift vp my ſword for to defend mée. And as I perceiued my ſelfe to approach ſo néere vnto my death, I looked if I could finde anie remedie againſt that miſerie, and to ſéeke it in my ſword there was no long hope, for the reaſons before alleadged. Wherefore going vppon the Rocke as well as I could, as GOD would I found a little hoale wherein I entered, and beeing within, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it to bee a Caue made into the Rocke: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the entrie were but ſtrayght and narrow, yet was there ſpace inough within to tourne and wynde my ſelfe, and vſe my weapons at pleaſure: whereinto there was no other entrie but that onely which I had luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely found out.</p>
               <p>It ſéemed the Lord himſelfe had ſent me thither, for by that onely meanes I recouered againe ſome part of my former ſtrength, which before I had almoſt vtterly loſt. Wherewith taking againe to my ſelfe freſh courage, and reuiuing my drouping ſpirites, I turned my face towards my enemies, placing the poynt of my ſword at the entrie of the Caue, and ſo began with moſt fierce Stoccadoes to defend my Fort.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>By that time the whole multitude of fiſhes had beſieged me round about, giuing moſt great flaſhes and aſſaults a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me in the water, and approching very neere vnto the mouth of the caue: but ſuch as ſéemed to bee moſt hardye, preſuming to eate in, I thinke eſcaped not ſcot free. For as I ſtood directly with my ſword againſt the entrie of the caue, they thinking to enter, fell vpon my ſword, and ſo loſt their liues: and others which with great furie approached néere vnto me, got their reward with blowes. All this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, made them not breake vp their ſiege: but in the meane time it waxed darke, and night approaching, made the fight ſomewhat to ceaſe, although they left not off manie times to aſſaile me, proouing whether I ſlept, or if by anie meanes they might perceaue me to be wearied and weake. This thus continuing, poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> being in this great extremitie, perceiuing my ſelfe aſſieged by ſo manie enemies, in ſo ſtrange a place, without all remedie or hope of reléefe: and conſidering, that my good conſeruator (I mean the wine) began by little and little to conſume with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, in place whereof the ſalt water entred, and that each houre I began to waxe weake, becauſe it was not poſſible for me to ſuſtaine my ſelf, my nature being altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto theirs, that remained and dwelt in the water: and that likewiſe my ſtrength failed me, by reaſon that of a long time I had not eaten any thing wherwith to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the ſame, but to the contrarie, laboured and trauelled my wearie bodie, as alſo, becauſe the water doth diſgeſt and conſume verie much: I ſtill looked for no other thing, than when my ſword would fall out of my weake &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hands, which ſhould no ſooner be perceiued by my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, but they would put me to a moſt cruell and bitter death, making their bodies my ſepulcher. All which by me well weighed and conſidered, and on the contrarie, not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any remedie or meanes of releefe, I turned vnto him to whom all good Chriſtians haue recourſe, recommending my ſelfe vnto him that giueth ayde and reléefe to all ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:9880:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
craue it at his hands: that was, the moſt merciful God our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Then I began afreſh to ſigh, lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and bewayling my former ſinnes, aſking mercie and forgiuenes for them, and committing my ſelfe vnto his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine will and pleaſure, I beſought him to deliuer me from that cruell death: with promiſe, that if it pleaſed him to giue me life, I would become a new man euer after. Then I made my prayers vnto the moſt glorious Saint <hi>Marie,</hi> his Mother and our Ladie, promiſing to viſite her in her houſes of <hi>Monferrat,</hi> of <hi>Guadalupe,</hi> and on the borders of <hi>France.</hi> After that, directing my ſupplications vnto all the Saints, but ſpecially vnto S. <hi>Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> and vnto <hi>Monſieur S Amador,</hi> which both haue power ouer the waters. This done, I rehearſed certaine oraiſons, as manie as I could remember (learned of my maſter) which with moſt great deuotion I vttered, beſides diuers other prayers, which haue force and power againſt the perills of the water. Which done, in the ende the Lord Ieſus, by the vertue of his paſſion, and by the force of the Saints prayers, and for the pitie of my great miſerie, which as then appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine eies, wrought in me a moſt maruellous and rare miracle, although in reſpect of his mightie power it ſéemed nothing: which was, that I being thus in manner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſoule, ſicke, and halfe choaked with the great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of water, which (as I ſaid before) had entered into my bodie, to my no little damage, and likewiſe being ſtiffe, and as it were dead with cold, that ſtill aſſailed me: which, as long as my preſeruer the wine remained in his force, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer once did feele. My ſorrowfull bodie being wearied, and as it were broken in péeces, by meanes of the anguiſh and continuall perſecution thereof, together with the diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of eating meate, I ſodainly felt my ſelfe to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the ſhape of a man (which I had béen, not féeling either hand or foote) vnto the verie ſhape and forme of thoſe which had and did at that preſent beſiege me round about. Whoſe ſhape when I perceiued my ſelfe to be changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I preſently knew them to be fiſhes called a Tonnie, and then I vnderſtood how they ſought my death, ſaying, This is the traitor, and the enemie of our ſauery and moſt ſacred waters: this is the aduerſarie, not onely of vs, but alſo of all other Fiſhes, which at this preſent hath made ſuch an execution and ſlaughter among vs, killing and murthering ſo great multitudes of our nation: it is not poſſible for him to eſcape from hence, but day once appearing wee will bee reuenged on him. Thus I heard the iudgement, which my maſters the fiſhes pronounced againſt mee, beeing a Tonny as well as they. In this manner being chaunged, I reſted and refreſhed my ſelfe in the Water, taking my breath, and finding my ſelfe as cléerely without paine or gréefe, as if I neuer had anie, waſhing my body both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without with that water, which then and from that time forward I found to be verie ſwéete and ſauerie, view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beholding my ſelfe, if I could perceiue anie part of my bodie that was not changed into a Tonnie: and ſo, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the caue in great eaſe and pleaſure, I thought with my ſelfe, that it would be good for me as ſoone as day came to get mee out from thence: but then I feared they would know me, and ſo my conuerſion ſhould be manifeſt vnto them. On the other ſide, I feared my iſſuing forth, diſtruſting in my ſelfe, that they could not vnderſtand me, and that I could not bee able to aunſwere them vnto that which they ſhould aſke mee, by which meanes my ſecrete might be diſcouered. For although I vnderſtood them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well, and that I perceiued my ſelfe to be of their forme and ſhape, yet I greatly feared to be among them. In the end, I determined the beſt way for mee was, that they ſhould not finde me within the caue: for they finding mee not to be of their companie, and <hi>Lazarus de Tormes</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found, they will ſtraight iudge me to haue ſaued him, and ſo will demaund an accompt of him at my hands. For the which cauſe it ſéemed beſt vnto me, that I going out of the caue before it were day, and thruſting my ſelfe among
<pb facs="tcp:9880:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them, being ſo great a number, peraduenture they would not ſée me, neither yet once finde me to bee a ſtranger: and as I determined with my ſelfe, ſo I put it in effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. How <hi>Lazarus de Tormes</hi> called a Tonny fiſh, went out of the caue, and how the Centinells of the Tonny fiſhes tooke him, and lead him before the Generall of the Armie.</head>
               <p>IN ſkipping out of the caue and leauing the rocke, I was preſently deſirous to proue my new language, and began with a loud voyce to ſay, I dye, I dye. Thoſe words ſcarce vttered by mee, the Centinell which held the watch ouer the poore ſinner <hi>Lazaro de Tormes,</hi> came vnto me, &amp; ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding about me, aſked me whom I ſerued. Sirs, ſaid I, I ſerue the Fiſhes, and thoſe which are called the valiaunt Tonnyes. Then ſaid they, for what cauſe didſt thou crye out ſo lowd? what is it that thou haſt ſéene or felt in our aduerſarie, whereby thou art ſo altered and perplexed, that thou knoweſt not vnder what Captaine thou ſerueſt? I ſaid they ſhould bring me before the Generall of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and there they ſhould know that which they demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Preſently thereupon one of the Tonnyes willed ten of the reſt to bring me vnto the Generall: meane while hee ſtayed behinde kéeping the watch, with the number of ten thouſand Tonnyes at the leaſt. I was excéeding glad to perceiue that they did vnderſtand mee, and ſayd vnto my ſelfe, He that ſhewed me this great grace, maketh no man lame.</p>
               <p>Thus we marched, and at laſt as daye began to appeare wee approached néere vnto the place where the great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie lay, whereas I perceiued ſuch an innumerable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Tonnyes, that I was abaſhed at the ſight. As ſoone as they knew thoſe which led me, they ſuffered vs to paſſe forward: and beeing entered into the Generalls lodging,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
one of my guard making humble reuerence, declared vnto him, where and in what manner they had found me, &amp; that I being aſked by Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> what I was, I anſwered him, that they ſhould bring me before the Generall: and for that cauſe they ſaid they had brought me vnto his Honour. The Captaine generall was an excellent Tonnie, fiercer and greater in body than the reſt: he aſked me, who I was, what was my name, vnder what captaine I ſerued, &amp; what I would haue, ſéeing I deſired to be brought before him? Whereat I ſtood in a manner confuſed, not knowing what name to ſaye I had, although I had beene rightly baptized, vnles I ſhould ſay my name was <hi>Lazaro de Tormes:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could I better tell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence I was, nor vnder what Captaine I ſerued, by reaſon I was but newly tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor knew not the ſeas, neither yet the large territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the perticular names of the ſame: in ſuch ſort, that letting paſſe ſome of the queſtions by the General pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto me, I anſwered him thus. My Lord, your honour being ſo valiant, as it is well knowen throughout the ſeas, it ſeemeth a great diſgrace vnto your Honour and vs all, that one miſerable weake man ſhould defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo long gainſt ſo puiſſant and mightie an Armie: and the more, conſidering his weake eſtate and abilitie, and the great power of the Tonnies. Saying further, ſéeing that I am one of your Honors ſubiects, and at your commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and of your Armie, I here preſent my ſelfe, with promiſe to get and deliuer vnto you his Armes, and other things that he hath: which if I doo not, I deſire for my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that you commaund me preſently to be cruely execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a traitor. Yet whatſoeuer I ſaid, I was ſure I made him no promiſe to deliuer <hi>Lazaro de Tormes</hi> vnto him, left I ſhould bring a foole to bed. This point proceeded not of mine owne mother wit, but I learned it of my maſter at ſchoole. Whereat the Generall tooke great pleaſure to ſée mee offer my ſelfe vnto ſuch a péece of ſeruice: by which meanes he deſired not anie farther matter of me, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb facs="tcp:9880:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
making me anſwere ſaid. It is verie true that to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the death of my ſouldiers, I determined to holde a ſiege about that traitor, and to take the man: but if (as thou ſaiſt) thou doſt aduenture thy ſelfe to enter the caue, thou ſhalt be well rewarded for thy labour: although it would gréeue me much, that venturing thy perſon in the Kings ſeruice and mine, thou ſhouldſt looſe thy life, as others haue done before thée: becauſe I eſtéeme much, and make great accompt of my valiant and ſtout Tonnyes, and ſuch as are more hardie than the reſt, I deſire to preſerue them before others, as all good Captaines ought to doo. My Lord, ſayd I, let not your excellencie ſtand in feare of any danger that may happen vnto me, for I hope to bring the matter to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect without the loſſe of one drop of my bloud. Séeing it is ſo ſaid hee, it is ſurely a great péece of ſeruice, for the which I meane to recompence thée well: and for that it is day already, I am deſirous to ſée how thou wilt accompliſh that which thou haſt promiſed. Thereupon hee preſently ſent vnto all the Officers of the Field, that they ſhould march forwards vnto the place where the enemie lay. It was a wonderfull thing to ſée ſo great and mightie a campe to remoue, and I ſuppoſe, that whoſoeuer had ſéene them, would haue béen abaſhed. The Generall cauſed me to go on the one ſide by himſelfe, by the way aſking me what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I meant to hold in the entring of the caue. I told him counterfetting and faining manie ſtratagems and deuices. Meane time we approached néere vnto the place where the Centinels ſtood about the Rocke, and to Captaine <hi>Licio,</hi> that had ſent me vnto the Generall: who at that time was in verie good order about the rocke, holding each place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the caue ſtraightly beſieged. And yet all this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, not one of them durſt once be ſo hardie as to approach néere vnto the entrie of the ſame, by reaſon that the Generall had ſent ſpeciall commaundement to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, thereby to auoyd the damage that <hi>Lazarus</hi> did vnto them: becauſe that at ſuch time as I was conuerted into a
<pb facs="tcp:9880:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Tonny fiſh, I let the ſword ſtand vpright in the entrie of the Caue, and in ſuch manner as I helde it in my hands when I was a man, which the Tonnyes ſaw, fearing that their enemie helde it in his hands, and that hee ſtood right before the entrie of the caue. As we approached néere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place, I ſaid vnto the Generall, it were good hee ſhould commaund thoſe that held centinell and ſiege about the caue to depart, and that he with al the reſt ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelues from thence; which was preſently done. I did that, becauſe they ſhould not perceiue the little labor I had to enter into the caue. Then I (being alone) gaue great and liuely flaſhes in the water, and ſkipping vp vnto the mouth of the caue, I made a ſhew of ſome great thing I ment to doo: meane time that I did this, the report went among them, that I had begun to enter into the caue, but ſaid they, he will be ſlaine as well as others (altogether as hardie and bold as he) haue béen: let him alone, for aſſure your ſelues, you ſhal ſée his luſtines well cooled in the end. In the mean time I made ſhow as though ſome reſiſtance had bin made againſt me out of the caue, &amp; that the enemie thruſt at me, as he had done at others, whereat I made as though I ſkipped with my bodie from the one ſide to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And as the Armie ſtood in this amaze, they had not the wits to perceiue that which in truth was not to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: ſometime I approached vnto the caue, and aſſailed it with moſt great force, making as though I fought, and then againe I retired as I did before: which I did onely to make a ſhew of great matter, where none was. After I had done this thrée or foure times, ſtanding ſomewhat diſtant from the caue, I began to roare with a loud voice, to that end the General and the whole Armie might heare me, ſaying: O miſerable man, thinkeſt thou that thou canſt defend thy ſelfe againſt the great power of our puiſſaunt Lord and and King, and againſt his valiant Captaine ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, with thoſe of his mightie Armie? Thinkeſt thou to eſcape from hence, without being puniſhed for thy great
<pb facs="tcp:9880:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
boldnes, and the great murthers, which by thy meanes haue béen done vpon our frends and companions? Yéelde, yéeld thy ſelfe (I ſay) a priſoner vnto the valiant and great Generall, and it may bee hee will bee mercifull vnto thée. Yéeld thine Armes, which haue ſo well ſerued thée at this preſent, and come forth of thy ſtrong Hold wherein thou art, for it will little auaile thée to tarrie there, and put thy ſelfe into his power, with whom for power none within the whole compaſſe of the ſeas may once compare. I, (as I ſay) giuing theſe great and threatening ſpeaches vnto poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> &amp; all to fill the eares of the hearers thereby to incourage them, as men are accuſtomed to doo, béeing a thing wherein they take much pleaſure: a Tonny came vnto me from the Generall, willing me to come preſently vnto him: with whom I went, and at my approaching, I found both him and all the reſt almoſt dead with laughter, and ſuch was the noyſe that they made, that one could not heare the other by meanes thereof: but as I appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, beeing much amazed at ſuch an alteration, the Generall commaunded that each man ſhould bee quyet: whereat ſome ſilence was made, although the moſt part of them began againe to laugh, till at the laſt, with much paine, the Generall ſaid vnto me: Companion, if thou holdeſt no other method in entring the Fort of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, than that thou haſt alreadie ſhowen, neither ſhalt thou accompliſh thy promiſe, nor I be anie thing the wiſer in ſtanding to truſt vpon thée: which maketh me the more to ſuſpect it, in that I haue onely ſéene thée to aſſaile the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the Caue, and yet thou didſt not enter: and more, that thou beginneſt to perſwade our aduerſarie by ſpeach, which euerie one can doo as well as thou. So that as farre as I and theſe the reſt of my Campanie can perceiue, thou wouldeſt be verie glad to be well rid of ſo dangerous an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereby it ſéemeth moſt apparant and euident vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that all this time is but loſt, and theſe words ſpent vainly to the winde, becauſe I am certaine by this meanes
<pb facs="tcp:9880:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thou canſt not in a thouſand yeares accompliſh that which thou deſireſt, or haſt ſaid that thou couldeſt doo: and for this cauſe wee laughed at thée, and ſurely our laughter is not without iuſt cauſe, to ſée thée ſtand prating vnto him, as if thou wert ſome iolly fellow: and then they all began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to laugh at me. With this I found mine owne want, and ſaid within my ſelfe, If God had not preſerued me to ſome other end than to féed thoſe fooles, the vnaccuſtomed manner of behauiour that I vſed as a Tonnie, would haue béen cauſe of my decaye: which was ſpecially by reaſon that I had onely their forme and not their nature. But I ſéeking to amend mine error, anſwered: My Lord, when anie man is deſirous to effectuate that which hee hath in minde to doo, it happeneth vnto him as it doth vnto mee. Whereat the Generall and all the reſt began againe to laugh, ſaying, Alas poore man thou art deceiued, for thou ſhouldeſt haue anſwered vnto mee (as it is true) that thou feareſt, that in ſtead of renting his cloathes, he will teare thy bodie. With that hee left off ſpeaking for that time. Wherewith I ſeeing that ſtill my want of behauiour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and perceiuing that with a few more of ſuch checks I might ſoone be mated, I began alſo to laugh with them for companie, but God knowes I grinned with no ſmall feare, which at that time I had: and therewith I ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Generall, My Lord, it may pleaſe you not to thinke that my feare is ſuch as ſome of you doo preſume, becauſe that hauing to doo with a man, you thinke that the tongue vttereth that which the heart meaneth: but it ſéemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that I ſtay ouer long to accompliſh my promiſe, and to take vengeance in your behalfe of this our enemie, wherefore with your Honours licenſe I would willingly craue that I might returne to make an ende of my enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. Thou haſt thy requeſt ſaid he. Then I with no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhame and feare returned towards the caue, thinking thereafter (as it touched me néere) to be wiſer and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter in my ſpeach. And approaching vnto the Caue, I
<pb facs="tcp:9880:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
made as though I had bene ſtriken, and faining to retire, I ſkipped ſodeinly vnto the entery of the hole, and tooke that with my mouth, which at other times I vſed to doe with my handes: which done, I ſtudied, thinking with my ſelfe, whether it were beſt for mee to enter into the Caue, or to go and deliuer the Sword vnto the Generall, to whome I had promiſed the ſame. In the ende I conſidered, that if I ſhould go in, I might peraduenture be accuſed of theft, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I had eaten him, ſéeing hee was not there to bee found, which had bene a thing worthie of puniſhment. At the laſt I turned my ſelfe vnto the Army, the which I prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to help me, becauſe they had ſéene me recouer the ſword, and yet to ſhewe more courage, hauing gotten it vpon the rocke, then when I tooke it at the mouth of the Caue, I ſkirmiſhed with the ſame, wreathing &amp; turning my mouth, looking on all ſides both backward and foreward, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto the Generall, with humble ſalutation, holding the ſword as well as I could, (by the hilts) in my mouth, I ſaid; Valiant Captain, Behold here the Armes of our cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell enemy, from this time forth there is no cauſe of feare, why we ſhould not enter into the Caue, ſéeing he hath not any thing wherewith to defend the ſame. You haue (ſaide he) done like a valiaunt Tonny, and aſſure your ſelfe you ſhall be well rewarded for ſo great a péece of ſeruice, and for becauſe with ſo great valour and hardineſſe, you haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſword, and that it ſéemeth vnto me, you can better ſkill of it then the reſt of vs, I pray you holde it ſtill vntill we haue gotten this vnhappie and wicked traitor into our hands. With that an infinit nomber of the Tonnies went vnto the mouth of the Caue, but yet not one of them durſt be ſo bold to enter into the ſame, becauſe they feared that he was not without a poniard, then I profered my ſelfe to be the firſt that wold venture for to enter, ſo that ſome of them would follow and aſſiſt me: and this I deſired, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I meant to haue witneſſes of my innocency, but ſuch was the feare whiche they had of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that not one of
<pb facs="tcp:9880:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them ſought to follow me, although the Generall promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed great gifts vnto him that ſhould ſecond me. The thing ſtanding in this point, the Generall aſked mee, what I thought beſt to bee done therein, ſéeing not one of them was deſirous to beare me companie in that dangerous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. I anſwered, that for his ſeruice I would venter to enter therein my ſelfe alone, ſo they would aſſure mee the entrie, and that they ſhould not feare to ſtand by me. Hée ſaid it ſhould be ſo, and if ſo be that thoſe which were there durſt not doo it, he promiſed to follow me himſelfe. In the meane time Capiaine <hi>Licio</hi> came vnto vs, and ſaid that he would enter in with me: wherewith I began to ſkirmiſh on all ſides of the caue with my ſword, and to giue diuers fierce prickes with the ſame, and at the laſt ſkipped in, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a lowd voyce, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoria, Victoria,</hi> God ſaue the the great ſea, with her great and puiſſant inhabitants of the ſame, and confound thoſe which dwell vpon the Land. With theſe cries (although but full euill fauouredly vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> (of whom I ſpake before) entred after me, who at that day wan much renowne, and recouered with mee much credite, in ſhowing himſelfe ſo hardie and valiant aboue the reſt: yet it ſéemed vnto me, that one wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was not ſufficient to diſcharge mee, and therefore not leauing the entrie of the caue, I deſired more helpe: but all in vaine was my requeſt, for the diuell take them all, not one of them durſt once venter to enter. And ſurely they were not greatly to be blamed therein, for I aſſure yee in my conſcience that I my ſelfe ſhould haue done as much, if I had thought the thing to bee as they tooke it, (for what ſhould a man doo but ſpeake the truth): but for mee, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred therein, as into mine owne houſe, knowing very well before, that there was not ſo much as a ſnayle within the ſame. Then I began to animate them thereunto, ſaying, O mightie, great and valiant Tonnyes, ſhow foorth this day your force and accuſtomed boldnes, ſéeing that ſuch an occaſion is offered, whereby you may win honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne.
<pb facs="tcp:9880:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Are you not aſhamed to ſhow ſo little courage? Know yee not that your Enemies will from hencefoorth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme but little of yee, when they ſhall ſée and vnderſtand your ſmall courage? With theſe and other things ſpoken vnto them by mee, the Generall himſelfe (although with more ſhame than otherwiſe) entered in, crying, Peace, peace: by which words I vnderſtood verie well, that hee brought not all in with him, ſéeing that in time of ſo great warres, he proclaimed peace. As ſoone as he was entred, he willed the reſt to enter, which I thinke entred full euill againſt their wills: but when they perceiued not poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> nor yet anie defence againſt them, although I gaue great blowes and thruſts againſt the ſides of the caue with my ſword, they were all amazed. And the Generall was aſhamed of the ſmall companie that approached to helpe me and Captaine <hi>Licio,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. How after that <hi>Lazarus</hi> with all the Tonnyes had entered in the caue, and finding nothing therein but <hi>Lazrroes</hi> cloathes, there entred ſo manie, that they thought to be ſmothered therein: and what remedie <hi>Lazarus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed for the ſame.</head>
               <p>SEarch hauing béen made round about the Caue, wee found the apparell of the valiant Tonny <hi>Lazarus de Tormes,</hi> for they were left behinde me when I was turned into a fiſh: yet when I ſaw them I was in no ſmall feare, doubting leaſt my poore bodie had béen ſtill within them, and that the foule onely had béen turned into a Tonny: but as God would I found not my ſelfe there, and then I knew aſſuredly, that both in bodie and ſoule I was turned into a fiſh. Yet I was not well in my minde, becauſe neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I felt no ſmall paine, and it gréeued mee in my verie fleſh, to ſée thoſe garments that had fitted my bodie ſo well beeing a man, to bee ſo iniuriouſly torne and plucked in
<pb facs="tcp:9880:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
péeces by thoſe which did it with ſo good a will, and yet I was conſtrained to do the like my ſelf, becauſe I would not ſéeme to vary from thoſe of my company, thereby offering occaſion to be perceiued. At this fight the Generall and the reſt being aſtoniſhed, and looking rounde about verie cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, yet not without feare, although they deſired to méete with that which they founde, after that they had well ſearched and compaſſed the litle Caue, the Captaine Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpake, aſking me what I thought as touching the not finding of our aduerſary there. My Lord ſaid I, without doubt, I thinke verely this was no man, but rather ſome diuel, which tooke the ſhape of a man vpon him, for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and domage; for that who euer ſawe, or heard it reported, that the bodie of a man could ſuſtain it ſelfe ſo long time vnder the water, or yet coulde doe as this man hath done, and in the ende holding him encloſed in ſuch a place as this is, and ſtanding ſo neare as we did, he to haue eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the ſight of vs all. I hauing ſaid my opinion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing readie to make an ende thereof, there happened a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daunger vnto vs, which was, that as the Tonnies that were without, began to enter into the Caue, they came in ſo faſt, perceiuing themſelues to bee deliuered of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and to get part of the ſpoile, as alſo to bee reuenged of the murthers, hee had committed vpon their companions and friends, that when we looked about vs, the Caue was ſo full, that from the very bottome vnto the toppe, men could ſcarce finde any ſpace within the ſame, but that all was full of Tonnies, and ſo heaped one vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, that we were almoſt all ſmothered to death: for as I ſaid before, there was no ende of their entering in, vntill ſuche time as the Generall began to deuiſe how he might remedie the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in ſuch ſort, that he perceiuing the neceſſitie of the caſe, and the great perill wherein wee ſtood, ſaide vnto me, My ſtout and valiant companion, what meanes ſhall we finde for to get out from hence with our liues, ſéeing as thou ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the daunger beginneth more and more to encreaſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:9880:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
yet we are all in a maner ſmothered to death? My Lord ſaid I, the beſt remedie will be, if theſe which are here before vs could giue vs place, that I might get vnto the entery of the Caue, and defend it with my ſword that no more might enter in, theſe that are in might go forth, and we likewiſe with them, al with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daunger. But that is impoſſible, becauſe there are ſo many Tonnies vpon vs, and you ſhall ſée, that all this notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they cannot let, but that ſtill there will more enter in, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he which is without, thinketh that thoſe that are here within, are diuiding the ſpoiles, and deſire their part thereof, ſo that there is but one onely remedie to helpe vs: which is, if for to eſcape, your honor thinke it good that ſome of theſe that are within ſhould die, becauſe that to make roome for your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it cannot bee done without hurt vnto the reſt: ſéeing it is ſo (ſaid he) it is good to ſaue the beſt and looſe the worſt, that all the reſt may reioyce. Séeing that you (ſaid I) doth commaund it as hauing authoritie, it may pleaſe your honor to diſcharge me in this action from all damage that may happen vnto me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. There ſhall not only (ſaid he) not any harme be done vnto thée, but alſo I promiſe thée, that for thy paines thou ſhalt bee well rewarded: for in ſuch extremities it is a great benefit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the armie that the Captain ſhould be ſaued, and I had rather ſaue one ſcale of my ſelf then any ſubiect vnder me. O Captains ſaid I vnto my ſelfe, which make ſmall account of other mens liues, ſo you may ſaue your owne, many there be that do as this Captaine doth, but how farre different are ſuche mens actions from that which I haue heard reported of one <hi>Paulus Decius,</hi> a noble Romane Captaine, when the Latins conſpired againſt the Romanes, and both the armies being readie to ioyne, the night before the battaile ſhould be, the ſaide <hi>Decius</hi> dreamed, that it was ordeined by the Gods, that if he died in the battaile, the Romanes ſhould ouercome and get the victorie againſt the Latins, and if otherwiſe hee were ſaued and eſcaped, then the Romanes ſhould bee ouerthrowne, and the firſt thing he did, (when the battailes began to ioyne) was to ſet himſelfe in ſuch a dangerous place, that he could not by any meanes eſcape with his life, becauſe the Romans ſhould be victors, and ſo they were:
<pb facs="tcp:9880:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but our great Generall Tonney, did not followe him in this pointe. Then I conſidering of the ſecuritie which hée promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, and the great neceſſitie that vrged me thereunto, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with the meanes I then might haue to bee reuenged of the euill entertainment and ſtraunge lodging wherein theſe wicked and peruerſe Tonnies had put mee. I began to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with my ſworde, and to ſtrike the beſt I coulde both on the left and on the right ſide, ſaying, Foorth, foorth, you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcréete Tonnies, whiche ſmother our noble Captaine in this Caue, and then ſtriking and thruſting both backward and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in a ſhort time, I diſpatched no ſmall number of them, not regarding, or reſpecting any one, but only Captaine <hi>Licio,</hi> who for that I perceiue his good will towards me in entring of the Caue, I bare ſome affection vnto him, and to ſay truth I loued him very well, whereby I loſt nothing, as hereafter ſhall bee ſhowne: At the whiche ſight, thoſe that were within the Caue, ſéeing the great ſlaughter, beganne to diſlodge, and looke with howe great a force they entered, they iſſued foorth with a greater. Which newes when thoſe that were without knew, and ſawe ſome of their companions iſſue foorth bléeding, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wounded, they ſought no more to enter, and by that meanes they left vs alone with the dead Tonnies, whereby I placed my ſelfe at the mouth of the Caue, and then beganne to giue diuerſe fierce thruſtes out of the ſame. And in my opinion I thought my ſelfe as nimble with my ſword which then I held in my téethe, as when I vſed to holde it in my hand.</p>
               <p>After that, I hauing diſpatched our Generall and thoſe that were with him out of trouble and ſmothering, they beganne to ſuppe of the water whiche at that preſent time was turned into blood: And likewiſe to teare, rent, and eate, thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable dead Tonnies that I had ſlaine. Which I perceiuing, beganne to beare them company, and yet it ſéemed newes vnto me to handle them in that ſort, although I had eaten of them before in <hi>Toledo,</hi> but not ſo freſhe as I eate them then: and in that manner I filled my ſelfe with great ſtore of ſwéete and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourie Fiſhe, not letting to doo it, notwithſtanding all the great and terrible threatenings, that thoſe which were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:9880:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
made againſt me for the damage I had done among them. Hauing ended our banquet, when the Generall thought it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient time, we iſſued foorth, I giuing him to vnderſtand of the euill will and meaning that thoſe whiche were without had againſt mée, that his excellencie might prouide for my ſafetie and ſecuritie. Hée going foorth well ſatiſfied and filled, (at which time they ſaid it is beſt hauing to do with great lords) cauſed it to bee proclaimed openly, that whoſoeuer were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies either in word or déede vnto the valiaunt ſtraunger Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that they ſhould die for it, and that they and their heires ſhoulde bee alwaies holden and accounted for Traytors, and that their goods ſhould bee confiſcated vnto the Kings vſe: for if the ſaide ſtraunger Tonny did them any damage or hurt, it was becauſe they were Rebelles, and had broken the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their Captaine, and by their negligent ouerſight, had put him in great daunger of death: With whiche Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation euerie one ſéemed to bee content, and agreed that thoſe which died in the Caue, by that meanes had well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſame, and that the liuing ſhould from thencefoorth put vp the quarrell, and liue in peace.</p>
               <p>This done, the Generall cauſed all the other Captaines, maiſters of the fielde, and vnder Officers, whiche had anie charge of the Armie, to bee called togither, willing as many of them as had not beene within the Caue, to goe in, and to diuide the ſpoyle they ſhoulde finde among them, which was ſoone done, for there were ſo many that they had ſcarce euerie one a morſell of a Tonny. They comming foorth, becauſe they though it good, that euerie one ſhould haue his part of the ſpoyle, proclaimed openly, that eache one might enter who woulde, whiche the common ſorte did ſoone performe, for anie thing that was to bee founde there, vnleſſe it were certaine droppes of blood, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> cloathes.</p>
               <p>Héere I haue ſet downe for a perpetuall memorie, the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of theſe Fiſhes, and howe farre differente the ſtate of man is, from this of theirs. For put the caſe that here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth there be diuerſe men to be founde dwelling, which ſéeke after ſome cunning ſort, and in ſome couetous maner
<pb facs="tcp:9880:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to deuoure their neighbours goods, which I doubt are more to be founde at this preſent, then hath bene heretofore, by reaſon that mens conſciences are now far larger than they haue bene in times paſt, yet there are none ſuch to be found that are ſo void of reaſon or humanitie, that they doo, or would eate their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors fleſh. Wherefore ſuch men as daily do complaine of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wrongs and iniuries done vnto them vpon earth, let them (ſay I) come vnto the ſeas, and they ſhall ſoone perceiue thoſe things to be bread and hony which they complaine of, in reſpect of that which is to be found among the fiſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſheweth what an euill rewarde the Generall of the Tonnies gaue him for his ſeruice, and of the friendſhip he entered into with Captaine <hi>Licius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVut returning vnto the matter, the next day after, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall being in his Chamber, tooke me aſide, and ſaid vnto me, Valiant and ſtout ſtraunger Tonny, I haue determined with my ſelfe, that thy good ſeruices and counſels ſhall be well rewarded, for if ſuche as thou art ſeruing as thou haſte done, ſhould not be rewarded, there would none be found in great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that would venture their perſons in any daungerous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: wherefore in reſpect thereof, thou ſhalt from henceforth be aſſured of our fauour and good wil, and withall thou ſhalt be fréely pardoned, of all the murthers and maſſacres by thée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vppon our ſouldiers and companions within the Caue, and in memorie of the good ſeruice thou didſt in my behalfe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering me from the perill of death, thou ſhalt poſſeſſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy (as thine owne proper good) this ſword wherewith thou haſt done vs ſo much damage, becauſe I ſée thou canſt manage it ſo well, (but yet with this prouiſo,) that if with the ſame thou ſhalt hereafter commit any violence, or do any wrong vnto our ſubiects, and the naturall Tonnies of our ſoueraigne Lord the King, thou ſhalt die for it, and herewith it ſéemeth vnto me thou art well rewarded, and from henceforth thou maiſt returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place from whence thou didſt come. And ſo ſhowing me
<pb facs="tcp:9880:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
no great good countenance, he left me, and went vnto the reſt of his companie. Wherwith hearing him vtter ſuch ſpeaches vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, I was ſo aſtoniſhed, that I ſtood almoſt without either ſenſe or féeling, becauſe I looked (at the leaſt) hee ſhould haue made me ſome great man (I ſhould haue ſaid a Tonny) for my good ſeruice, giuing me a charge during my life of ſome great Signiory in the ſea, as he before had offered vnto me. O <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> ſaid I vnto my ſelfe, thou didſt diſtribute and ſpred among thy ſouldiers ſuch ſpoyles and riches as thou wonſt from thine enemies: I haue likewiſe heard of <hi>Caius Fabritius,</hi> a Romane Captaine, in what manner hee rewarded and crowned thoſe which firſt did aduenture themſelues to enter into the Liſtes: and thou <hi>Gonzago Hernandes</hi> General of the Spaniards, didſt giue other manner of rewards vnto ſuch as ſéeking to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the braue ſouldier in the ſeruice of their King, and to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thine honour, did put themſelues into all hazards of the field: for that all ſuch as did ſerue and follow thée, to how many of them didſt thou giue great rewards? that of poore and néedy ſouldiers thou madeſt them both valiant and rich: not as this vnworthie Tonny doth, rewarding me with that, which in <hi>Cocodouer</hi> had coſt mee but thrée royalls and a halfe. Let thoſe therefore that complaine of great Lords vppon earth, comfort themſelues herein, ſéeing that in the déepe ſeas there are ſuch ſmall rewards beſtowed by great Lords. I ſtanding in this ſort, thus penſiue and ſad, Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> perceiuing it, came vnto me, and ſaid: Sir, to ſuch as truſt in great Lords &amp; Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, it hapneth oftentimes as it doth vnto thée: for they, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in néed of other mens aid, doo make manie great promiſes, but being deliuered out of danger, they doo not once ſo much as remember their promiſe made. I my ſelfe am witnes of thy great and good ſeruice, and of all thou haſt ſo valiantly done, as he that hath béen preſent by thée, and I ſée likewiſe the euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that thy valour and proweſſe hath receiued, beſides the great perill wherein thou art: wherefore I am deſirous thou ſhouldſt vnderſtand, that manie of theſe which are heere preſent before thée, doo among themſelues conſpire thy death. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not that thou depart out of my companie, for that I am bound to doo for thée as for mine owne childe, and to fauour
<pb facs="tcp:9880:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and aid thée: not onely with mine owne, but alſo with the aid of my frends, to the vttermoſt of our powers, for it ſhould be a moſt great damage, to looſe ſo valiant and hardie a fiſh as thou art. For the which his great curteſie, I rendred him moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thankes, withall accepting of his gentle and courteous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer made vnto me: in lieu whereof I preſented my ſmall abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie vnto him, offring to be readie at all times to doo him what ſeruice I could: and wherewith hee ſéemed to be ſo well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that preſently he called vnto him fiftéene hundred Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes of his Regiment, willing them from that time forward to take charge to guard me, and to beare mee companie in ſuch manner as vnto himſelfe: ſo that neither night nor day they did once depart from me, &amp; that they did verie willingly, for there were not manie among them that hated mee: and as I ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there was no ſmall number among the reſt of the great Armie, which did beare mee good will, by reaſon that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held me at ſuch time as we fought to ſhow forth my great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and force. In this manner Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> and I entered into league and frendſhip, which we ſhewed by no ſmall ſignes one vnto the other, as after you ſhall heare. Of him I learned manie things touching the cuſtomes and manners of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Seas, together with the names and prouinces, kingdomes and ſigniories of the ſame, and the names of the Lords and Gouernors thereof. In ſuch ſort, that in ſhort ſpace he made me as experient in them, or rather more, than the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Tonnyes themſelues: for that I could better diſcourſe vppon them, than they were able to doo. Not long after, our Campe brake vp, and the Generall willed that each Captaine ſhould depart, and that within two months after all the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſhould repaire againe vnto the Court, for it was the Kings pleaſure. Wherewith my frend and I departed, and all his Companie, which (to my iudgement) were about ten thouſand Tonnyes: among the which there were not aboue ten Females, and thoſe were labouring Tonnyes, ſuch as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Souldiers are accuſtomed to waſh and get their liuing. There I ſaw the deuiſes that thoſe Fiſhes vſed to finde out meate to ſuſtaine themſelues: which is in this manner. They ſcatter and ſpread themſelues abroad on all ſides in certain pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
each Companie holding the circuite of a league and more, and if it fortune that two Companies doo chaunce to méete, they turne their heads one againſt the other, making forward to ioyne together, and all the Fiſhes which they take in the midſt betwéene them, are ſure to die, and to bee torne in péeces with their téeth. And in this manner doo they hunt twice or thrice euerie day, as they chaunce to iſſue foorth. Thus we fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our bellies with great ſtore of ſwéete and ſauerie fiſhes, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refying the olde Prouerbe, which ſaith, that the great fiſhes deuoure the ſmall: for that if in our circuite we found anie greater fiſhes than our ſelues, wee preſently gaue them a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſuffering them to paſſe away without anie brabling, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they deſired to remaine with vs, helping vs to kill &amp; eate other Fiſhes, according vnto the common ſaying, Hee that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no paines for his liuing, is not worthie to eate. At one time among others, we tooke certaine Cuttle fiſhes, whereof, the biggeſt among the reſt I ſaued and kept for my ſlaue, and made him my page to beare my ſword: by which meanes I had my mouth at libertie, and not cumbred with the ſame, and my Page turning one of his ſinnes backward (in manner of a ring) carried it verie eaſely at his pleaſure, ietting and brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging among the reſt. In this manner wee trauelled for the ſpace of eight Sunnes, (for that in the Sea the dayes are ſo called) at the ende whereof wee drew néere vnto the place, where my frend and thoſe of his Regiment kept their wiues and children: of whom wee were receiued with moſt great ioy, and euerie one went home vnto his owne houſe, leauing me in the Captaines lodging, being after the ſea manner ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtately.</p>
               <p>We being entered into the Captaine <hi>Licioes</hi> houſe, he ſayd thus vnto his Wife: Gentlewoman, the gaynes which I bring you of this Voyage, is to haue gotten for my frend this gentle Tonny, which héere you ſée. The which purchaſe I make no ſmall accompt of: wherefore I pray you let him bee welcome vnto you, and giue him as good entertainment, as you were accuſtomed to doo vnto my brother: for therein you ſhall doo mee a ſingular great pleaſure, becauſe I honour and admire his vertues.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>She was a verie faire Tonny, &amp; with a verie good grace made him anſwere: Sir, aſſure your ſelfe it ſhall be done as you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and if anie default be found in me, it ſhall not be for want of good will. Whereat I made an humble reuerence, and fell downe, deſiring her to giue mee her hands that I might kiſſe them: which I ſpake ſome what ſoftly, ſo that (as it chaunced) they neither ſaw nor heard my folly. But I ſaid vnto my ſelfe, what a foole am I, to deſire to kiſſe her hands, that hath nothing but a tayle? The Tonny gaue me a ſwéete kiſſe, willing me to riſe vp, and ſo I was moſt curteouſly receiued of her: and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto her my ſeruice, it was verie well accepted of, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſo wiſe an anſwere of her againe, as of ſo honourable a Gentlewoman might be giuen. In this manner we remained there certaine dayes in great pleaſure, I being verie well vſed and intertained by thoſe Gentlemen, and wayted vppon by his ſeruants. In the meane time I taught the Captaine to play at ſence, although I neuer had learned in all my life: and yet I did it very nimbly with my ſword, which he praiſed very much as likewiſe a brother of his called <hi>Melo,</hi> a verie braue Tonny. Reſting thus at mine eaſe, one night beeing alone in my bed, and thinking vpon the great fauour and frendſhip I had found in this fiſh, my great frend, deſiring if occaſion might bee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to doo ſomewhat for him, as part of a recompence of the great debt which in that behalfe I ought him: at the laſt there came vnto my minde a great ſeruice that I might doo, which in the morning I imparted vnto him: which he tooke in good part, becauſe it was not to be diſliked, and which ſtood him in great ſtead, as hereafter ſhall be ſhowen. The thing was thus, that I ſéeing him to be ſo wel affectionate to armes, told him that he ſhould doo well to ſend to the place where our ſhipwracke hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and that there hee ſhould finde manie ſwords, ſpeares, ponyards, and other manner of Armes, and that they ſhould bring away as manie as they could finde: for that I was min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to take the charge vppon mee to learne our Companie the managing of them with much dexteritie: which if I brought to paſſe, his Companie ſhould thereby be the moſt ſtrong &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant aboue all others, and which the King and all the Sea would moſt accompt of, becauſe that by that meanes it would
<pb facs="tcp:9880:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
be more worthie for ſtrength than all the reſt ioyned together, whereby hee might obtaine much honour and profite. This ſéemed vnto him to be the counſell of a verie good frend, for the which he gaue me moſt heartie thankes: and preſently there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon putting my counſell and aduice in effect, hee ſent in all haſt his Brother <hi>Melo</hi> with ſixe thouſand Tonnyes vnto the place by me alleadged, who verie ſhortly after with great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence returned againe, bringing with them an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſwords and other weapons, whereof diuers were all ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: which ſhould ſéeme to haue laine in the ſea ſince the time that the valiant Captaine <hi>Don Luigo de Moncada</hi> ſuffred ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke in that place. The Armes beeing brought, they were deuided amongſt thoſe Tonnnyes that ſéemed vnto vs to be the moſt nimble &amp; of beſt courage among them. And then the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine on the one ſide, his Brother on the other, &amp; I as the chiefe Maſter of Defence, taught ſuch as deſired to be expert in their weapon: ſo that we imployed our whole time in learning them to manage their Armes, and to defend themſelues therewith. Whereby in ſhort ſpace there were ſome among them that could giue the thruſt, the croſſe blow, and the reuerſe: as for the reſt that dealt not in their weapons, wee appointed them to hunt and ſéeke for victualls: and the women wee learned to ſcowre our weapons, by a fine inuention that I deuiſed: which was that they ſhould thruſt them into the ſand, and draw them forth againe ſo long, vntill they waxed bright. In ſuch manner, that our companie being ioyned altogether, hee that ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that part of the ſea, would thinke he ſaw a great battaile in the water. In the ende, by this meanes there was almoſt not one of the Tonnies but began to be very expert in his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon. Hereupon we entred into counſell, and in the ſame it was agréed, that we ſhould make a perpetuall league &amp; amitie with the cuttle fiſhes, whereby they might come and liue among vs, becauſe with their large ſinnes they might doo vs great ſeruice to beare our Armes: and ſo it was done, and they were glad of it, becauſe they ſaw we tooke them for our frends, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them: the which (as I ſaid before) might ſerue our turnes in that point without anie paine or trouble vnto them. About this time, the ſpace of two moneths appointed by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:9880:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for the Captaines repaire vnto the Court began to draw néere: at the end whereof, the Captaine generall ſent comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that they ſhould come thither. Whereupon <hi>Licio</hi> began to make preparation for his iourney, and betwéen him and I it was debated, whether it ſhould be good for me to goe with him to the court, to do my humble dutie vnto the king, that he might know me: but we found it not conuenient, conſidering the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſéemed to beare me no great good wil, and that he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commanded me to returne vnto mine owne countrie: for the which cauſe, the matter being throughly debated in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Melo,</hi> brother vnto Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> (a Tonny of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good wit) and of the no leſſe wiſe Tonny his wife, their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent was, that I ſhould ſtay there with her. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he determined to go in all ſpéed, and to take but few of his men with him, &amp; being at the Court, he would informe the king of me, and of my great valor, and vpon the Kings anſwere we ſhould procéed. This being agréed vpon among vs, the good cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Licio</hi> departed on his iourney with very néere a thouſand Tonnies, his brother <hi>Melo</hi> &amp; I with al the reſt ſtaying at home in our lodgings: and at his departure from me, taking me aſide he ſaid vnto me, My verie frend, I muſt of force let you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I depart from hence with no ſmall gréefe, by reaſon of a dreame I had this laſt night, I pray God it fall not out to be true: but if to my euill fortune it ſhould happen to be true, I pray you that you will take it in good part, and thinke vpon that which you haue giuen me in charge, and hereof I pray you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to know anie farther at this preſent, becauſe it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for you nor me. I beſought him much to declare the ſame vnto me, and the rather, becauſe at his departure from his wife, his brother &amp; the reſt, he gaue me a nod with his head, (although verie ſadly) leauing me verie ſorrowfull and heauy. He being gone, I could not but thinke vpon the matter, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things ran in my minde touching the ſame: &amp; among the reſt, I ſuppoſed this one to be it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peraduenture he vnto whom I was ſo much beholding might thinke, that the beautie of his wife, (which moſt commonly is not matched with the greateſt honeſtie) would blinde me ſo much, that I could not ſée how the ſea doth abhorre ſo great a wickednes. But that good law is at,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this day much corrupted on the earth, &amp; in the ſea it is the like, but it is no meruaile. In this conceipt I continued long, and in the end I deuiſed a meane whereby he might be aſſured of me, and my loyaltie no way ſuſpected: which was thus, that I and her brother in law being with her, (after ſome ſalutations and comforts offred vnto her on our parts, thereby to put her out of the melancholy humor which we perceiued to be in her, becauſe of her huſbands departure, and the rather to behold him ſo ſad and heauie, although that he hid it both from her and me at his departure from vs) I told <hi>Melo</hi> that I deſired to be his gueſt, if be thought it good, becauſe I could not be merrie, being alway in companie of women: &amp; rather than I ſhould be troubleſome vnto her, I would leaue the houſe. She was preſently readie to make me an anſwere, ſaying, that if ſhe found anie meanes of comfort, ſhe thought it would be by reaſon that I was in her houſe, and at her commandement, ſhe knowing verie well the great loue and affection that her huſband bare vnto me, &amp; that at the time of his departure from her, he gaue her not any grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter charge, than of the care that ſhe was to haue of me, althogh I ſuſpected not what the cauſe was: for our thoughts did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſagrée. In the end, I thinking that it might be with the Tonny fiſhes, as it was with me in the ſame caſe, touching my wife <hi>Eluira,</hi> and my maſter the Prieſt, could neuer be in quiet, but deſired rather to be with her brother in law, and whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I went to viſite her, I brought him alwaies with me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Lazarus</hi> telleth what happened vnto Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> his frend at the Court, by meanes of the Captaine generall.</head>
               <p>BEing ſometimes hunting, and ſometimes exerciſing our weapons, within eight dayes after my frends departure, newes was brought vs, which made vs the moſt ſorrowfull fiſhes in the ſea. Being thus, that when the Captaine generall vſed me ſo hardly, as I told you before, he willed me to depart out of the Army, ſaying, that thoſe Tonnies which found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues agréeued at me, becauſe of my offence committed againſt them, would be reuenged: and afterwards he had commaunded
<pb facs="tcp:9880:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
certaine Tonnies, that finding me alone from al company, they ſhould preſently kill me, and for no other cauſe more than that it ſéemed vnto him (as it was very true) that I would be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his cowardlines, for other cauſe there was none, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where deſert is it ought to be recompenced: but God preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this miſchiefe, putting (as I thinke) into <hi>Licioes</hi> hart, the fauor he ſhewed me. Which being knowen vnto the Generall, he bare him likewiſe moſt great hatred &amp; euill will, affirming and ſwearing that that which <hi>Licio</hi> did vnto me, was for to vex and gréue him: and knowing verie wel he had but a hard wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of him, becauſe he was with me, when the General entring into the caue cried, peace, peace. This together with that which the good Captaine (and better than he) had done vnto me, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to procure this miſchiefe againſt him, and as hee came vnto the Court, he went preſently with great complaints vnto the King, accuſing him as a traitor, ſaying, that one night as the ſaid <hi>Licio</hi> was Captaine of the guard, and held the néereſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinell vnto the caue, for a great ſumme of money which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him by the enemie, that he might eſcape, he left his watch. Which he affirmed to be true by diuers witneſſes, and euen ſo God helpe him as he told the truth: for that <hi>Lazaro de Tormes</hi> could not giue any thing, vnles it wer a number of their heads that lay dead at his féete. And going on with his falſhood, ſayd, that he had brought from ſtrange places, a moſt cruell and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Tonny, the which had ſlaine a great number of his Armie, with a ſword that he carried in his mouth: wherewith he plaid his part ſo nimbly, that it was impoſſible for him to doo it, except he were ſome diuel, that for the deſtruction of the Tonnies had taken their ſhape vpon him: and that he perceiuing the great damage which the wicked Tonny had done, baniſhed him from the armie vpon paine of death, and that the ſaid <hi>Licio,</hi> in deſpite of the King and of his royall crowne, as alſo in deſpite of him, had entertained the ſaid Tonny in his companie, &amp; giuen him aide: for the which cauſes he affirmed him to be a traitor, and to haue incurred the danger of the lawes, and in reſpect thereof, he ought to be deliuered into the hands of the Iuſtices to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for his offences, that by him others might take example, that hereafter none might break the Kings commandements.
<pb facs="tcp:9880:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The King being thus wrong enformed, and worſe counſelled, giuing ſo much credit vnto his wicked Captaine, with two or thrée falſe witneſſes that ſwore as he had taught them, and with a proofe made in the abſence of the partie accuſed, the ſame day that Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> arriued at the Court, altogither innocent and ignorant of the matter, he was commanded to be taken and put into a cruell dungeon, with a great chaine about his necke: and commiſſion giuen vnto the Captain Generall to kéep him ſafe; and to ſée him puniſhed according vnto his deſert, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently prouided more then thirtie thouſand Tonnies to watch him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. How that <hi>Lazarus</hi> vnderſtanding of his friend <hi>Licios</hi> impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, was verie much greeued thereat, and all the reſt of his company; and what order they tooke for the ſame.</head>
               <p>THeſe ſorrowfull and dolefull newes, were brought vs by ſome of thoſe that went with him, declaring vnto vs how they had charged him in ſuch ſort as I ſayd before, and in what maner he had béen heard, and that it would go hardly with him, by reaſon that all the Iudges which had to do in the cauſe, were ſuborned by the Generall, ſo that as they thought, the matter procéeding in ſuch order as it did, he could not long eſcape from a moſt cruell death. (At that time I called to minde the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commonly vſed, and ſayd vnto my ſelfe, When ſhalt thou ende thy aduentures? when thou ſhalt haue finiſht a thouſande miſfortunes on the land, and many more in the ſeas.) At this their ſpéech, there beganne among vs a great lamentation and crie, but in my ſelfe a double ſorrow, becauſe that on the one ſide I ſorowed for my friend, and on the other ſide, I lamented mine owne eſtate, for that wanting him, I had no hope of life, being then both in the middle of the ſeas, and of my enemies, altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without comfort and forſaken: for it ſéemed vnto me that all the company complained on me, and that with moſte iuſtly and by good reaſon, for that I was the only cauſe that they muſt loſe him whom they deſired. Wherewith I ſayd, You my Lord departed from me in great ſorow, without once imparting your grief vnto me, now I ſée well that you prognoſticated my great
<pb facs="tcp:9880:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
loſſe, without all doubt ſayd I, this is the dreame that you my good friend dreamed, this is that grief which at your departure leauing me, you left vs withall. And thus euery one mourned and lamented vnto himſelfe, till at the laſt I ſpake in preſence of them all. My Lady and you my Lord and friends, that which the ſorrowfull newes hath conſtrained vs to do, hath béen iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, for each of vs by outward ſigne, doth ſhow his inward griefe, but ſéeing that this our firſt motion is paſt, as it were in a moment, it is good reaſon my Lordes, ſéeing that with teares and complaintes, our loſſe is not recouered, that we giue order preſently for the beſt remedie that may be deuiſed therein: and the ſame well wayed and conſidered, to put preſently in effect, ſéeing that as theſe men ſay, the occaſion of ſpéeding the matter which by thoſe men that hate vs is miniſtred vnto vs, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the ſame. To this the faire &amp; chaſt Tonny his wife, ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding many teares from her gracious eies, anſwered me. All of vs (moſt valiant gentleman) do very wel perceiue &amp; know that your reaſons are moſt true, as alſo the ſoden neceſſitie which at this preſent offreth it ſelf vnto vs, verifieth the ſame: wherfore if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theſe gentlemen and my friends were all of my opinion, we ſhould all referre our ſelues vnto you, as vnto him whome God hath indowed with a moſt cleare &amp; perfect iudgement, for ſéeing that <hi>Licio</hi> my Lord, being ſo wiſe &amp; learned, did put you in truſt with his moſt earneſt &amp; waightie affaires, and therein followed your counſell, I do not thinke that I erre any thing herein, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am but a weake &amp; ſimple woman) in deſiring you to take the charge vpon you, for the prouiding &amp; ordeining of that which ſhall be conuenient to be done, for the ſafetie of him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you with ſo ſincere a loue, and to the comfort of this his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull wife, which by this meanes you ſhal alwaies bind vnto you.</p>
               <p>This ſaid, ſhe returned vnto her complaints, and al we did the like. <hi>Melo</hi> &amp; other Tonnies were with the captaines wife, and at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent agreed in one conſent with her, giuing me the charge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enterpriſe, offring themſelues to follow me, and to do all whatſoeuer I would command them. I ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I was in dutie bound to do it, and to take vppon me all care &amp; trouble for him, that for me was in ſuch miſery, tooke the matter vpon me,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſaying vnto them, I knew very wel, that euery one of you could do it better than I, but ſéeing that it pleaſeth you ſo to appoint it, I am very well content therwith. They thanked me, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was preſently agreed vppon, that wee ſhould make the ſame knowne vnto all the Regiment, which was preſently done, ſo that within thrée daies after they were all gathered togither. I choſe out for my Councell, twelue of the richeſt among them, not reſpecting their wiſedoms if they were poore, becauſe when I was a man I had ſéene that ſufficiently done in diuers aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, wherein many cauſes of importaunce were handled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as I ſay) they looke not whether they be apparelled with wit, ſo they be apparelled in ſilke. Theſe being choſen out, one of them was <hi>Melo,</hi> and an other the Captaines wife, a woman of great wiſedome, a thing very well knowne both by land and ſeas.</p>
               <p>This done, we ſent vnto all the company that they ſhould dine, and then repaire vnto vs in order of battaile, the armed with their armes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt with their bare bodies, when they were come, I cauſed them to be numbred, and we found them to bee in all the number of tenne thouſand one hundreth and nine Tonnies, all fighting men, without counting women, boyes and olde men, whereof fiue thouſande of them were armed, ſome with Swordes, other with Launces, Ponyardes, and Kniues, all which tooke their oathes vppon my tayle (vnder the whiche they put their heades according vnto their accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med manner,) although I laughed in my ſelfe to ſée their pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ceremonie,) that they woulde doe as I ſhoulde commaund them, and woulde thruſt in their weapons, and thoſe that had none their Téethe, into whome ſo euer I ſhoulde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde them to doe it, procuring with all their power and force if it were poſſible to ſet their Captaine at libertie, their dutie and loyaltie vnto their ſoueraigne King alwayes reſerued.</p>
               <p>Wée agreed likewiſe in our Counſell of Warre, that the Captaines wife ſhoulde (beeing amongſt vs,) bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the number of one hundreth of the beautiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of all the other female Tonnies, among the reſt one of them
<pb facs="tcp:9880:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
was a ſiſter of his, a Gentlewoman of great beautie, and verie well proportioned,, and of our army we made thrée eſquadrons, one of all the vnarmed Tonnies, and the other two, of thoſe that beare armes, I led the vantguard, with two thouſand fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth armed Tonnies, and <hi>Melo</hi> led the rereward with as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more: the diſarmed, with the carriages being placed in the middle, hauing with vs our Pages, (ſpoken of before,) that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our ſwordes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. How <hi>Lazarus</hi> and his Tonnies being in order of battel, went vnto the Court, minding to deliuer <hi>Licius</hi> out of priſon.</head>
               <p>IN this manner, as I ſaide before, we marched forwardes, in great haſte, giuing charge vnto ſuch as we thought good, for the prouiſion of victualls for the armie, becauſe they ſhould not diſorder themſelues. In the way I queſtioned with thoſe that brought vs the newes, of the ſituation of the Courte, and the place where our Captaine was kept in priſon, meane time, at the end of thrée dayes we were within ten miles of the Court, and for becauſe we marched in ſo new and vnaccuſtomed order, if our comming ſhould bee knowne, we might bee preuented of that we went for, we agreed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we would not march any further vntill night came, willing certaine of thoſe Tonnies that had brought vs the ſorrowfull newes, to go before into the Cittie, and as ſecretly as they could, learne how the caſe ſtood with our Captain, and hauing ſo done, preſently to return vs the newes: wherof ſome of them returned and brought vs the worſt newes we could deſire. Night being come, it was agreed that the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines wife and her women, with <hi>Melo</hi> and fiue hundred Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies diſarmed, of the beſt and oldeſt among them, ſhould goe ſtraight vnto the Court, and as they wel could do it, they ſhuld beſéech the King that it would pleaſe him to examine the cauſe of her huſband and his brother, and that I and all the reſt wold place our ſelues in a wood full of trées and rockes, within two miles of the Citie, where the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> King ſometimes went to ſollace himſelfe, and there we would remaine vntill ſuche time wee ſhould ſée by our aduiſe from them, what were beſt to bee done. We preſently went vnto the wood, which we founde verie well
<pb facs="tcp:9880:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
prouided with great ſtore of fiſhes, vpon the which we fed, or to ſay the truth, filled our ſelues at our pleaſures, and all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany did the like. And the faire and gentle Tonny by morning arriued at the Citie, and preſently went vnto the court, where ſhe ſtaide a long time at the gate, vntill the King roſe, to whom they declared the comming of that gentlewoman, in the ende, by meanes of the importunate ſute ſhe made vnto the porters, they ſuffered her to enter in, that ſhee might ſpeake vnto the King. But the King, that perceiued well her ſute, returned her an anſwere, that as then he had no time to heare her, ſhe ſéeing that he deſired not to heare her by word of mouth, cauſed a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in very good forme to be drawne by two Counſellors, that pleaded for <hi>Licio,</hi> wherin ſhe beſought him to remit iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Licio,</hi> ſeeing he had appealed vnto his maieſtie, and the reaſon why, for that he was the day before condemned to die, by the Iudges of the land, as we vnderſtood, by our aduiſer, ſaying his highneſſe knew very well, that her huſband had bene falſly accuſed, and vniuſtly condemned, and that his highneſſe would cauſe the inditement to be peruſed, and the iudgement with the execution of the ſentence to be ſtaied. Theſe and other things were conteined in the petition, which ſhe deliuered vnto one of the porters, and withall tooke her chaine of gold with a Iewell hanging thereat from about her necke and gaue it him, praying him to ſtand her good friende, and with teares from her eyes, to conſider of her dolour and grief, and not to reſpect the ſmal gift. The Porter very willingly tooke her petition, but more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly her chaine, promiſing to do for her the beſt he could, and in very déed, his promiſe was not in vaine, for that the petition being red before the King, he from his owne mouth (ful of gold) vſed ſuch perſwaſions vnto his highneſſe, withall ſhowing him of the teares and lamentations that the Captaines wife made for her huſband, at the Pallace gate, that therewith he mooued the King to pitie her eſtate, and ſaid. I will that you goe with this woman vnto the Iudges, and will them to ſtaie the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the iudgement, becauſe I am deſirous to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed touching certaine pointes concerning Captaine <hi>Licios</hi> accuſation. With the which commiſſion, the Porter verie glad to haue ſped ſo well, came vnto the ſorrowfull gentlewoman,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
aſking her a reward for his earneſt ſolicitation, which ſhe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly gaue him, and then without farther delay, they went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudges lodging, but as her hard fortune fell out, in going thither, they chaunced to méete in the ſtréete with <hi>Don Pauar,</hi> (for ſo was the cauſer of our trobles named,) who being accompanied, went to the court, but as he eſpied the gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with her captain, and vnderſtood who they were, knowing likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Porter, craftily ſuſpected what their meanings wer, ſo that very diſſemblingly he called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Porter vnto him, aſking him whither he went with that company, who preſently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it vnto him: he ſéeming to like it well, told the Porter how the caſe ſtood touching the captaine (although it was all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) ſaying that he liked wel the kings procéeding therin, bicauſe <hi>Licio</hi> was a braue ſouldier, and there was no reaſon why hee ſhould bee executed without further examination of the cauſe; ſaying further, that the Iudges were at that preſent in his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and ſaid they came thither to aſke my counſell in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherupon I was now going to the court for to ſpeak with the king, whereas they attend my returne, but ſéeing that you bring a diſpatch, let vs goe backe againe, and declare the kings pleaſure vnto them, and going by the way, he called one of his Pages to him, to whome very pleaſantly he ſaid, that he ſhould with all haſte goe vnto the Iudges, and will them preſently to cauſe execution to be done vpon captaine <hi>Licio,</hi> becauſe it was the kings pleaſure, and that they ſhould execute the ſame either within the priſon, or elſe at the gate thereof, without leading him vnto the common place of execution, meane time that I hold the Porter here in talke with me, the Page did as he was commaunded, and drawing neare vnto the Generalls lodging, the Traitor tooke the Porter in with him, and ſayd vnto <hi>Melo,</hi> and his ſiſter in lawe, that they ſhould be of good comfort, and ſtaie there, while he went in and ſpake with the Iudges, and that from thence they would goe all togither to the priſon to ſée <hi>Licio,</hi> and to comfort him, giuing him that which he ſo long had expected, and that he ment to go thither himſelfe with them, but the vnfortunate woman by good hap was enformed of the great treaſon of the captain general. And although he had greater ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred vnto the good captain <hi>Licio,</hi> then compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the teares
<pb facs="tcp:9880:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and lamentations of his wife, yet for an outward ſhowe hee ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to fauour her requeſt. For when as the cruell traitor called vnto his Page, willing him to go and cauſe <hi>Licios</hi> execution to be diſpatched, as God would, one of her ſeruants heard him, and told it vnto the captaines wife, which the wicked generall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not, whereat ſhe fell in a maner dead, vpon the necke of brother in law, ſtanding next vnto her. Which aſſoone as <hi>Melo</hi> vnderſtood, he preſently cauſed 30. Tonnies of his company to depart with all ſpéede, and to declare vnto me in what point and iminent danger the caſe ſtood with <hi>Licio,</hi> who like faithfull and diligent meſſengers, did within ſhort ſpace make vs acquainted with thoſe ſorrowfull newes, which they brought vs, crying with loude voices, Arme, Arme, you, O you valiant Tonnies, for our captaine ſhalbe preſently executed to death, by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and deceit of the traitor <hi>Don Pauar,</hi> againſt the will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our king, and ſo in briefe rehearſed vnto vs, all that I ſhowed you before: whereat I preſently cauſed the drums to be ſounded, and in all haſte my Tonnies were readie with their mouthes armed, vnto whom I made a pithie Oration, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole procéedings, to the end that as good and valiant ſouldiers they ſhould ſhewe their courages againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ayding and ſuccouring their captaine in ſo extreame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, who anſwered all with one voice, that they were readie to follow me, and to do their endeuours in that behalfe: which their anſwere being ended, we preſently beganne to march thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but hee that had then ſéene <hi>Lazarus</hi> the Tonny marching before his ſouldiers, would haue iudged him a valiant captain. To conclude, we entred into the towne and beſieged the kings palace, and by force tooke <hi>Licio</hi> out of their hands, ſlaying great nombers of them. Which the king perceiuing, willed <hi>Licioes</hi> wife who was then at the court, to ſue to the king for <hi>Licio,</hi> to returne vnto her huſband and tell him, that if he thinke good, I would haue him to diſſolue his ſiege from about his palace, and ſuffer his ſubiects quietly to go home to their houſes, and to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to come hither againe, and deliuer her meſſage vnto the councell, and then ſhe ſhould haue Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>The Captains wife with this anſwer departed not, but taking time when it ſerued, ſaide vnto the king, My Lord, neither my
<pb facs="tcp:9880:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
huſband nor yet his company, do hold any ſiege about your roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſon, neither likewiſe haue they entered into any houſe, but that of <hi>Don Pauar,</hi> ſo that the inhabitants of this citie, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not iuſtly complaine, that there hath bene any iniury done vnto any of them in their houſes, wherefore what it pleaſeth you to commaund as touching them, it ſhall be done, for, for that cauſe I was ſent vnto your grace. For God is our iudge, that neither <hi>Licio</hi> nor his company haue any other meaning or intent, but as good and faithfull ſubiects ought to haue. Woman ſaide the king, for this time I can ſay no more vnto thée. Wherewith ſhe and her women making humble reuerence, with moſt gracious behauiour and comely ſort departed from the preſence, whiche the kings pleaſure being knowne vnto vs, we preſently in good order departed the cittie, ſtaying in the wood, but yet not verie hungry, becauſe we fell to eating of our enemies dead bodies, commaunding the diſarmed Tonnies to carry as muche with them, as might ſuffice our army for the ſpace of thrée or 4. daies, leauing neuertheleſſe as much within the citie, as ſufficed the citie and the court likewiſe: thoſe that liue of the ſpoile wiſhed no other thing of God, then that euery eight daies, there might happen the like among them, light vpon whom it would. The citie being diſcharged of our troopes, the citizens repaired again ech man to his houſe, finding them as they left them. The king commanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the captain generals treaſure ſhuld be brought vnto him, which was ſuch and ſo much, as there was not anie king within the ſeas, that had the like, and then the king had ſom reaſon to miſtruſt his traiterous dealing, becauſe he might well ſuppoſe that it was not poſſible for him to get that hee had gotten, by good means, but by ſtealth. Then he cauſed his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to bee aſſembled, who ſaide vnto the king, that if it were as <hi>Licio</hi> ſaid, he then had not much offended in that actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpecially becauſe his highneſſe had commanded iuſtice ſhould not be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vntil further enquiry were made: and to confirm y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, the Porter that had the meſſage in charge, declared the ſubtile practiſe that the Generall vſed with him: and how he deceiued him &amp; brought him to his owne houſe, ſaying the Iudges were there, and that he let them not depart from thence, and what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence he made towards the court.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Further, he was ſhowed by the Sheriffes, that the Captain ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall had ſent them word, that his Highnes commanded them that they ſhould preſently cauſe execution to bee done, and the better to diſpatch it, they ſhould not lead him thoough the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſtréetes, but doo it before the priſon gate: which they beléeuing to be true, had deliuered him to be executed. In ſuch maner, that the King knew and perceiued his Generals fault, and the more he looked into the matter, the more he perceiued it to be true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. How the Captaines wife returned againe vnto the King, and of the good anſwere ſhe brought.</head>
               <p>ALL this while we ſtayed that day and the next night in the wood, not greatly in quiet: and the next day after the Captaines wife with her Companie went againe vnto the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace: and to auoid tediouſnes, the King by that time was in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quietnes, receiuing her verie curteouſly, and ſaying, Good woman, if all my ſubiects had ſo wiſe and diſcréete wiues, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture they ſhould increaſe their honor and wealth, and I accompt my ſelfe happie. I ſay this, for that in truth I ſéeing your diſcretion and wiſe reaſons, haue therewith appeaſed my anger, and you thereby haue deliuered your huſband &amp; his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie from my wrath and heauie diſpleaſure: and for becauſe that ſince your being here I haue béen better informed than I was, tell him that vpon my word he may come to the Court, with all his frends without anie perill or danger. But for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding of tumults and ſpeaches, at this preſent will him from me that he kéep houſe as a priſoner, vntill I ſend him word vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the contrarie: and in the meane time I pray you come hither and ſée vs, becauſe I take great pleaſure to ſée and behold your perſon, good behauior, and pleaſant ſpeach. Whereat the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines wife kiſſed his taile, giuing him heartie thankes for the great grace and fauour he ſhewed, as ſhe full well could doo it, and ſo returned vnto vs with a moſt ioyfull anſwere: although ſome of vs thought it not conuenient to be done, ſaying it was but ſubtilly &amp; politikely done, thereby to get vs into his hands. In the end we agréed as loyall ſubiects, to accompliſh the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb facs="tcp:9880:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of our King, truſting vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I meane our mouthes, when our loyaltie ſhould bee brought in queſtion. Whereupon we preſently remooued vnto the Citie, and entred therein, finding in the ſame man is frends, which as then ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es themſelues, perceiuing our enterpriſe to be wel taken, and effectuated, but before they burſt not make anie ſhow thereof, as the olde ſaying is, When Fortune turneth and ſendeth thée aduerſitie, then thy frends are ſhaken and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from thée: for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie ſheweth who be frends, and who are foes. Being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, we retired vnto one end of the Citie wherein leaſt people were, where ſtood houſes great ſtore, but moſt part without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, beeing the houſes of ſuch as wee had ſlaine, there we lodged as néere as wee could together: in the meane time giuing commiſſion that not one of our band ſhould walk abroad into the Citie, that the Princes will might be fulfilled. Meane time the Captaines wife, went euerie day vnto the Court to viſite the King, as he had commaunded, with whom ſhe became a great frend: but as farre as I could perceiue, although all ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med cléere water, yet the beautifull <hi>Luna</hi> paid for all, for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with her ſiſter in theſe viſitations, (and as it is a common ſaying, Such pilgrimes, ſuch ſaints) the King wan her fauour ſo well, that in the ende he obtained her loue: which I verely thinke ſhe did not with the conſent of her ſiſter. Which Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Licio</hi> knew verie well, for that in a manner he deliuered it vnto me, aſking my counſell therein. I told him that in my opinion the matter was not great, ſpecially becauſe it would be a great helpe, and the principall occaſion of procuring our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And ſo it fell out: for that the faire Gentlewoman <hi>Luna</hi> was ſo priuie with the King, that within eight dayes after his royall coniunction, fall out what would, we were all pardoned and acquited: and the King releaſing her brother in law, ſent word that we ſhould all come vnto the Court. Beeing there, <hi>Licio</hi> kiſſed the Kings taile, which he offred him verie willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and I did the like, although with an euill will, as béeing a man, and to kiſſe in ſuch a place. Then the King ſaid vnto vs: Captaine, I being informed of your loyaltie, and not hearing anie thing vnto the contrarie, therefore from henceforth I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don you, with all your companie, frends and ſeruants, which in
<pb facs="tcp:9880:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the enterpriſe paſt did aid and aſſiſt you: and becauſe hereafter you ſhalbe here attendant at our Court, I giue vnto you all the houſes with the goods therein, of thoſe that (by the permiſſion of God) loſt them, together with their liues: giuing you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſame office that our Captaine generall had: and from henceforth I will that you exerciſe the ſame, as one that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well how to vſe it. Whereat we fell downe before him, and our Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> went &amp; kiſſed his taile once againe, giuing him great thankes for his liberall rewards, ſaying, that he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in God to doo ſuch ſeruice in the ſaid office, that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhould think it well beſtowed. The ſame day the King was informed of poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> the Tonny, although at that time I was ſo rich, &amp; ſo glad to ſée them frends, that me thought I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was better pleaſed. The King among diuers queſtions, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked how I found out the inuention of our armes. I anſwered him to his content. Then he aſked with what number of fiſhes I and my companie durſt incounter? I anſwered, the Whales excepted, I could ouercome all the fiſhes in the ſea. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon he appointed next morning to ſée vs all muſter before him. Next day <hi>Licio</hi> our Generall and I, with all the reſt of our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med companie went out, where I found a very good inuention, although the ſouldiers vſe it here at this preſent. I made them place themſelues in order, and ſo we paſſed before his Highnes, making a ring: which although the Coronell <hi>Villalua</hi> and his companie could do it better, and in brauer manner, yet in the ſea they hauing not ſéene anie eſquadrons made, it ſéemed ſtrange vnto them. After that I made a battaile of our armed Tonnies together, placing the faireſt and beſt armed in the firſt rankes, willing <hi>Melo</hi> with all the diſarmed, and with thirtie thouſand other Tonnies to come forth and ſkirmiſh with vs: who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed vs about on al parts. But we placing ours in good order, and holding cloſe together, began to defend our ſelues ſo well, and to ſtrike and hurt them in ſuch ſort, that all the ſea had not béen ſufficient to haue entred within vs. The king ſéeing that I had told him truth, and that in ſuch ſort we could not be hurt, called vnto <hi>Licio</hi> and ſaid, This your frend hath maruellous great ſkill in armes: it ſéemeth vnto me that in this manner we might conquere and ouercome the whole ſeas.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>It is moſt true as your Grace ſaith, ſaid our Captaine gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and as touching the good induſtrie of the ſtrange Tonny, my good frend, I cannot beléeue or be perſwaded otherwiſe, but that he commeth from God, and was brought into theſe parts for the augmentation of your Highnes honour, together with your lands and dominions, which your Grace may verie well beléeue: for the qualities and parts within him are ſuch, and ſo excellent, that I am perſwaded there is not anie one able to declare them in briefe: for he is the wiſeſt &amp; diſcréeteſt Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that is at this day in the ſea, with all vertuous and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, likewiſe moſt true, and verie faithfull, indued with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manners and behauiour, ſuch as I neuer heard ſpeake of before: and to conclude, there is nothing in him tending vnto euill. In ſaying thus much of him, your Highnes muſt not thinke that I ſpeake it by reaſon of the good will I beare him, but onely becauſe I know it to be moſt true. Truely ſaid the King, that Tonny is much bound vnto God, vpon whom he ſo liberally beſtoweth his graces and benefites: and becauſe you report ſo well of him, it is good reaſon we ſhould doo him honor, ſeeing he is come into our Court, wherefore I would haue you aſke him, if he be minded to remaine here with vs, wherevnto I would you ſhould perſwade him in my behalfe: and it may be he ſhall not repent him of our companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. How <hi>Lazarus</hi> agree to ſtay at the Court, and was of great cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and verie ſecret with the King.</head>
               <p>THis agréed betwéene them, the Generall tooke vpon him to declare it vnto me, and the King returned vnto the Citie, and we likewiſe. Being come home, the Captaine tolde mee what had paſſed (as touching me) betwéene the King and him, and how he deſired that I would ſerue him, with other things, In the end, I being intreated (with my great honour) conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereunto. Now behold I pray you, your Crier of wiues in <hi>Toledo,</hi> made the chiefe man in the Kings houſe, with charge to rule and gouerns the ſame: and goe &amp; tell it for a ieſt. Then I gaue thankes vnto God, that my affaires waxed daily better,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſought with all diligence to pleaſe the King, ſo that in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpace I fell into ſuch credite with him, that in a manner not anie thing whatſoeuer, were it of great or ſmall importance, but it paſſed through my hands, or was done by my counſell. This done, I thought it not conuenient to ſuffer ſuch as had deſerued puniſhment to eſcape: becauſe I knew verie well, how and in what manner <hi>Licioes</hi> ſentence had bin vniuſtly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, although the king had paſt it ouer in ſilence, by reaſon the Captaine generall was a Fiſh of great accompt and of great power. Wherevpon it entred into my minde to ring the bells againe, and ſaid vnto the King, that there had a matter of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor happened to him of late, which were not worthie to bee kept in ſilence, becauſe it was a meanes to cauſe iuſtice to bee done, as a thing appertaining vnto his Maieſties ſeruice, that ſuch as are faultie ſhould be puniſhed. Which his Highnes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently committed vnto me, as he did all other things: and I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuored my ſelfe ſo well therin, that I cauſed all the partakers in the ſame to be apprehended, when they little thought of anie ſuch matter: who being put vnto the racke, confeſſed they had ſworn falſly in the cauſe, whereby <hi>Licio</hi> was condemned: and aſking them wherefore they did it, and what the wicked Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gaue them to doo it, they anſwered, that hee had not giuen nor promiſed them anie thing, neither were they his frends or ſeruants. O ſenſles and miſerable ſinners, O contentious men ſaid I, which complaine that your aduerſaries condemne you by falſe witneſſes, which they proued againſt ſuch times: come come I ſay vnto the ſea, and you ſhall behold the ſmall reaſon you haue to complaine vpon earth: for that if the ſame your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie doo produce falſe witneſſes, either he giueth or promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them ſomwhat for their paines, or elſe they wer his frends or acquaintance befor that time, for whom he promiſeth to doo the like: but theſe vnfaithfull fiſhes are neither by promiſe, by reward, nor frendſhip mooued thereuntoo, wherfore they are ſo much the more to be blamed and worthie of puniſhment, and ſo they were hanged. I vnderſtood farther, that the Clearke by whom the cauſe was pleaded, did not preſent nor yet take anie writing that was brought him in the behalfe of <hi>Licio,</hi> neyther admitted anie one to ſpeake that deſired to anſwere for him. O
<pb facs="tcp:9880:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
great ſhame ſaid I, which although if be ſuffred on earth, that the Clearkes be fauourable, yet with more honeſtie they take the writings, although they put them not into the Court, but rather ſay they be loſt: but this is the verie act of the diuell. The like was found in the Iudges, for that I knew it could not bee vprightly done, that the Sentence was ſo ſoone giuen: wherein I blamed the Iudges much, ſaying vnto them, that a plea in a manner for two ſtrawes is not commonly ended in a yeare, and ſome not in ten, nor yet twentie: and you diſpatch a matter touching the life of an honourable Fiſh in one houre. Whereunto they could not anſwere me ought to excuſe theyr fault: but the King ſent expreſſe commaundement, that hee would haue the matter diſſembled withall as touching them, becauſe it concerned his royall authoritie: and ſo I did, but ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I well perceiued and ſaw, that the gracious and mightie hand of him that humbleth when he will, and exalteth whom it pleaſed him, ruled among them, &amp; likewiſe in the wicked Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: for where couetouſnes and enuie entreth, it corrupteth all things. For the which cauſe the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> puniſhed a wicked Iudge moſt gréeuouſly, cauſing him to be executed, and after flean, whoſe ſkin hee nayled vp ouer the ſeate of Iuſtice, placing the Iudges ſonne in his fathers ſeate: whereby the Barbarian King did verie well prouide in moſt ſtrange man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that no Iudge after that time ſhould be corrupted. To the ſame end, it is ſaid by a wiſe man, That where affection raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, reaſon hath no place: and that the good Lawier did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit verie few cauſes vnto the Iudges, but rather let them bee determined by law, becauſe the Iudges are manie times cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, either by loue, hatred or guifts: whereby they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to giue manie vniuſt iudgements. For which cauſe the Scripture ſaith: <hi>O you Iudges take no giftes, which blinde the wiſe, and ſubuert the words of the iuſt.</hi> This I learned of my good maſter, with all the reſt of my experience in the law: who (as it is reported) was better learned, than either <hi>Barto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> or <hi>Seneca.</hi> But to returne vnto my firſt purpoſe. I told ye the King ſent word it ſhould be ſo, although it went wholly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my minde. In the meane time, the Generall by the Kings commaundement, had a voyage to make, which was
<pb facs="tcp:9880:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with a great Armie to inuade the Sturgeons, whom wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ouercame, making their King tributarie: for the which he deliuered hoſtage, with condition to pay yearly for a tribute vnto our King a great ſumme of money, and withall to deliuer him one hundreth female Sturgeons, &amp; one hundreth males: which male Sturgeons becauſe they are a daintie fiſh, the king eate them at his owne table, &amp; the females he kept for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. After that, our General went againſt the Porpeſes, which he ouercame, &amp; brought vnder our ſubiection. Wherewith the number of our armed Tonnies grew ſo great and puiſſant, that we held manie kinde of fiſhes in ſubiection vnder vs, all which became tributaries and gaue pledges, as we ſaid before. Then our Captaine (not being contenced with the victories paſt) ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe againſt the Cocodriles, which are a kinde of moſt fierce fiſhes, and liue ſometime in the ſea, and ſometime on the land, with whom we had manie battailes: and although wee loſt ſome, yet for the moſt part he bare away the victorie. But it was no meruaile that we loſt ſome, becauſe (as I ſaid before) thoſe kinde of fiſhes are verie fierce &amp; cruell, great bodied, with great téeth and long tuſkes, wherewith they tare in péeces as many of vs as they could reach into their pawes: and yet for all their fiercenes, we manie times put them to the worſt, vnles if were ſomtimes when they ſaw themſelues ouer-preſſed by our Tonnies, then they forſooke the water, and took the land, and ſo they eſcaped. Which our Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> perceiuing, in the end left them, after he had ſpoyled great numbers of them: and hee himſelf likewiſe receiued great damage, and loſt the good <hi>Melo</hi> his brother: which cauſed no ſmal gréefe throughout the whole Armie. But our comfort was, that he died like a valiant Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: for it was reported vnto vs for a truth, that before they kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, he in perſon with his ſword (wherewith he was very nimble) killed more than a thouſand Cocodriles, &amp; yet they had not killed him, if it had not chanced, that they flying, and he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, he ſodainly fell vpon the land, &amp; there ſtayed, by which meanes (not being able to be ſeconded by his companie) the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie tare him in péeces. In the end, good Captaine <hi>Licio</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the warres, the moſt renowned fiſh that then liued in the ſeas, bringing with him great &amp; rich ſpoyles, which he gaue
<pb facs="tcp:9880:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wholly vnto the King, without taking anie thing for himſelfe. At his returne, his Highnes receiued him with ſuch counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and entertainment, as belonged vnto a fiſh that had done him ſo great ſeruice and honour, and withall beſtowed moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall rewards vpon him, as alſo vnto thoſe that had followed him: in ſuch manner, that euerie one found himſelfe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and pleaſed. And the King to ſhew the greater fauour vnto <hi>Licio,</hi> mourned for <hi>Melo</hi> his brother the ſpace of eight dayes, and ſo did we al. Your worſhip muſt vnderſtand, that the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning among the fiſhes, is, that when they are ſad and mourne, during that time they ſpeak not, but onely by ſignes aſke what they deſire to haue. And this is the manner that is obſerued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as their huſbands, wiues, children, or frends doe die, they mourne in that ſort as I ſaid before, and kéep it ſo ſtraightly, that it is holden for a great ignomie, and that the greateſt that may be found within the ſeas, if whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they mourne they chance to ſpeake, vntill ſuch time as the King ſending vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, willeth them to leaue mourning: and then they ſpeak as they did before. I heard it reported among them, that a Lord (for the death of a Ladie whom he loued, and kept as his frend) mourned in his owne Countrey for the ſpace of ten yeares, and for all that the King could doo, he might not cauſe him to leaue off mourning, becauſe that at ſuch time as he ſent him word to leaue off, he ſent word to beſéech his Grace, to cauſe him to bee killed, rather than leaue off mourning: which he could not do. And which is more, I was tolde (wherein I tooke great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to heare it) that his ſeruants perceiuing his long ſilence, ſome of them at a month, others another month, and other ſome at two months, as they deſired to ſpeake, forſooke his houſe, ſo that in the end he had not one left: and here with his mourning continued ſo long, that although he had deſired to leaue it, hee knew not with whom to ſpeake. When they tolde me this, I called to my remembrance diuers talkatiue men, with whom I am verie well acquainted, who neuer leaue talking, but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as one tale is ended, they begin againe. And many times, becauſe they would not looſe companie, they cut off their tales in the middle, and begin others, and ſo continue vntill the very night come vpon them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they muſt néeds leaue company, or els
<pb facs="tcp:9880:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they would neuer haue done, and the worſt is, that theſe men do not perceiue how much they offend God and the world here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and I thinke are little leſſe, then troubleſome vnto the diuel himſelfe, and he that will be wiſe, let him flie the companie of theſe fooles, becauſe like requireth like, for their paines, I wiſh they were vaſſalls vnto this Barron: and that during their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad with him, his friend might die, that I might be reuenged on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. How the King and <hi>Licio</hi> determined to marry <hi>Lazarus</hi> vnto the faire Ladie <hi>Luna,</hi> and how they were married.</head>
               <p>BVt returning vnto our matter, the mourning, and ſorrow, holden for the death of <hi>Melo,</hi> being paſt, the king ſent word that with all ſpéede the number of armed Tonnies ſhould bee new ſupplied and increaſed, and that they ſhould go ſéeke more armes, which was preſently done. At which time it ſéemed good vnto the king to marry me, to ſome one whom he thought good, and therupon he dealt with <hi>Licio</hi> about the ſame, vnto whom he committed the matter, but he would willingly haue bene quit of the charge, becauſe he knew ſomewhat by her, but for that it pleaſed the king, he durſt not otherwiſe doo: ſo he brake the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto me, being not a little aſhamed to do it, ſaying: that he ſawe and knew I deſerued more honour, as my déedes witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but the king had expreſly commanded that he ſhould be the mariage maker. In the end, the matter being at that point, it is my good fortune, ſayd I vnto my ſelfe, a nayle is not good to play at tennis withall, and a plague of ſuch a ball as cannot be taken but at the ſecond rebound, and ſéeing it pleaſeth God it ſhall be no otherwiſe, and that it is for my profite and aduancement, it is reaſon that I climbe from a prieſt vnto a king. In the ende I did it, and my mariage was ſolemnized, with ſo great triumphs and feaſtings, as if it had bene for a prince, being honored with the degrée of a vicount, that the king gaue me with her, which if I had it here vpon earth, would do me much more good than in the ſea, in the end from the baſe or meaneſt Tonny, my name roſe vnto a Signior. In the manner my ſignory led a tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant life, married very richly with my faire and new wife, the
<pb facs="tcp:9880:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Ladie <hi>Luna,</hi> but much better with my king, not forſaking his ſeruice, deuiſing ſtill howe I might pleaſe and content him, ſéeing I found my ſelfe ſo much bounde vnto him, ſo that there was no time by me omitted, wherein I made him not merrie, howeſoeuer it fell out, but ſtill I tooke care not to ſay any thing whereby he might be greeued or angry, hauing alwaies in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, how litle they are eſtéemed and accounted off with great Lordes, that tell them the truth. Withall remembring the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment that <hi>Alexander</hi> gaue vnto the Philoſopher <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> for declaring the truth vnto him, &amp; by this meanes I ſped not ill: beſides, I behaued my ſelfe in ſuch ſort vnto both great and litle, that they ſought my friendſhip almoſt as much as the kings. At the ſame time I though to frame &amp; confirme the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the ſea, like vnto that of the land, whereupon I aduiſed the king, and tolde him it were conuenient that ſéeing hee bare the burthen of all, he ſhould reape the profite, and it was thus: for that as then the Crowne had no other rentes or reuenewes then only the thirtieth part of all things that were ſolde, and when hée helde warre for a iuſt cauſe concerning his Country, they gaue him the fiſhes neceſſary and conuenient for the ſame warres, and paide for them, and only tenne fiſhes for his owne table euery day, I brought it to paſſe, that when they fiſhed they ſhould euery one giue him as much, and that it ſhould be a cuſtome as it is vpon the lande, and that they ſhould allow him <hi>50.</hi> fiſhes euery day for his owne table: I cauſed it likewiſe to be ordeined, that if any of his ſubiects were called a <hi>Don,</hi> vnleſſe he were ſo by lawful and liniall diſſent of patrimony, he ſhould pay a certaine ſum for a fine vnto his highneſſe, and this ſtatute I thought to be conuenient, becauſe the pride of the fiſhes is ſo great, that both good and bad, riche &amp; poore, all are <hi>Dons,</hi> as <hi>Don</hi> here, and <hi>Don</hi> there, <hi>Don</hi> when, and <hi>Don</hi> where: I did this, calling to minde the commendable behauiour of the women of my country, that if any chance to fall into that degrée, either ſhe ſhalbe the daughter of an honeſt houſholder, or of a ſquier, or els be married with ſome that is written worſhipfull, or vnto ſome other man of qualitie: for before they be ſuch, and of good welth, they call them not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> title of <hi>Don,</hi> but in the ſea, not ſo much as the daughter of a meane artificer, or a begger (if ſhe marry a
<pb facs="tcp:9880:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
man, although he be no Officer at all,) but they preſume with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in eight dayes after to put the name of <hi>Don</hi> vpon their tayles, as if that name of <hi>Don</hi> would make them frée from being the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſhoneſt parents, and of thoſe that had no ſuch titles, and as though many of them ſhould not bee aſhamed, leaſt they giue cauſe to haue their fathers taken out of their graues, and the memory of them to be again renued, and ſo their neghbors might laugh at them, and at their worſhippes, which they take vpon them, knowing it not to be verie ſounde, but therein they ſhowe themſelues to bee the more fonde and light headed. It ſéemed good vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king to ſet it at a high rate, wherby in ſhort ſpace ſéeing it coſt money, there woulde not bee many <hi>Dons</hi> founde. Of theſe things, and of the newe Impoſitions moſte profitable for the king, I enformed his highneſſe. And hee perceiuing my great care and dilligence in his ſeruice, was not ſlacke in rewarding mée, but rather became more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and bountifull vnto mée. At the ſame time I thought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my poore Squier of <hi>Teledo,</hi> or rather vppon his wiſe ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, when as I complained vnto my ſelfe, that I coulde not finde any Gentleman of account with whom I might be, and if I chanced to find one, I vnderſtood him to be very nigardly and ſparing: Then he told me of that, which I after vſed in the ſea, as a thing very profitable for mee, ſpecially one pointe therein, whereof I was very carefull, whiche was, that I tooke great care not to ſay any thing vnto the king that might offend him, and as it is a great pointe of wiſedome, I altogither followed his humor, vſing great curteſie, and ſhewing great fauour, vnto ſuch as he fauoured, although they nothing deſerued it, and to ſuch as hee liked not of, I vſed them hardly, ſpeaking euill of them, although I founde it not in them, and not refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to do for any were they neuer ſo badde. Remembring the ſayd <hi>Caliſtines,</hi> that for ſaying the truth vnto his maiſter <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the great, he cauſed him to bee cruelly put to death, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his death it might be eſtéemed a life, ſéeing it was for ſo iuſt a cauſe, but now no man vſeth it, but all ſéeke to liue in ſuch manner, that I bent my ſelfe as much as I could vnto that humor, and by this meanes my ſoppe fell into the hony, and my houſe was filled with rich riches, but although I was a Fiſh,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I had the vnderſtanding of a man, and the accurſed couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which at this day raigneth ſo much in man, for that a beaſt hauing his naturall foode, deſireth nor ſéeketh not any more. As the Cocke careth not for all the pearles in the Eaſt, if hee may haue his belly full of corne, nor the Oxe for all the gold in <hi>India,</hi> if he haue graſſe inough, and ſo is it with all other beaſts, only the beaſtly deſire of man is neuer ſatiſfied, ſpecially if it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with couetouſneſſe. I ſay this, becauſe that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the riches I had, (as there was not almoſt any king in the ſea, that had more, yet I was ſo pricked forewarde by that gréedie couetouſneſſe, and not with any lawfull meanes, that I cauſed ſome to go vnto the gulphes of <hi>Leon,</hi> and <hi>Yerro,</hi> others I ſent vnto the banckes of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> where diuers ſhips full of men wer caſt away, and to ſuch places wher any battels had bin fought vppon the ſeas, from whence they brought mee great quantitie of gold, ſo that I thinke they brought me at the leaſt fiue hundreth thouſand Dollors, (a kinde of Spaniſh mony) the king laughed when he ſawe me ſo reioyce, and to lie tombling vpon my mony, and aſked me what thoſe vaine things meant, ſéeing they were neither to be eaten nor yet to be carried about me, whereat I ſayd vnto my ſelfe: If thou kneweſt what they meane as well as I do, thou wouldeſt not aſke me ſuch a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but I anſwered him, that I meant to vſe them for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherewith he was ſatiſfied, but after I came againe to dwell on earth, as I will ſhewe you, a plague of them all for any that I euer ſaw, and if I had al thoſe here that were broght me in the ſea, I ſhuld haue no néed of any man, but then I muſt be forced to kéepe them in ſome other ſuch déep and ſecret place, leaſt I might happen to loſe them. At that time I deſired, if it had bene poſſible, to finde a ſhip that would take and lade them in, (although I ſhould giue the halfe part for the fraught,) and deliuer the reſt to my <hi>Eluira</hi> in <hi>Toledo,</hi> that with ſome of them ſhe might marry my daughter, for I was wel aſſured that there were many that would not refuſe her, being the daughter of a Crier. And with this deſire, I ſkipped twice or thrice after ſhips, that came from the Weſt, crying vnto them, aboue the water, that they might hearken vnto me, thinking they would vnderſtand me, and imagine my meaning, and although they
<pb facs="tcp:9880:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were not faithfull meſſengers to carry the treaſure, or ſome part thereof, vnto <hi>Toledo,</hi> wherewith they might profit men, and do them good withall, yet it would content my minde, for the loue I beare vnto mankinde, but when I called them, or they perceiued me aboue water, they preſently caſt hookes and dartes at me, to kill me, wherewith I turned and went againe vnto my houſe, ſometimes I wiſhed that <hi>Toledo</hi> were a port of the ſea, that I might fill it with riches, for that I doubted not but my wife and my childe ſhould get ſome part thereof. And with theſe and other thoughts and imaginations, I paſſed my time, and ſpent my life in the ſea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAIP. XI. <hi>Lazarus</hi> going to hunt in a wood, hauing loſt his companie, he found the Truthe, and ſpake with him.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Being by fortune ſtaied from my company, found the <hi>Truth,</hi> which tolde me that ſhe was the daughter of God, and that ſhe had deſcended downe from heauen vppon earth, for to liue there, and do good vnto men, and how ſhe had not left any place vnſought, but had viſited all eſtates both great and ſmall, and although that in ſome great mens houſes ſhe founde ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, others thruſt her cleane out of their doores, which their ingratitude perceiued by her, ſhe ſaide, had cauſed her to withdraw her ſelfe into a rocke in the déepe ſea, ſhe tolde me of many maruellous things, that had paſſed among all manner of men, which if I ſhould write vnto your worſhip, it would bee ouer long, and out of the matter, touching my troubles, when it pleaſeth your worſhip to haue the whole diſcourſe that paſſed betwéen vs, it ſhall be ſent you, I being come home, ſhewed the king what had paſſed betwéene me and the <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. How <hi>Lazarus</hi> departing from the Truth, going with the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Tonnies to bring forth their yoong, he was taken in the Fiſher mens Nets, and turned againe into a man.</head>
               <p>GOing very chéerfully vnto the Court, being greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted with the words that the Truth had vſed vnto me, I
<pb facs="tcp:9880:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
liued for a time verie merely in the ſea, and then the time drew neare, that the female Tonnies ſhould bee deliuered of their yoong, of that voyage the King willed me to goe, becauſe he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſent ſome ſtrength with them, to defende them, and at that time <hi>Licio</hi> was ſicke, if hée had béene well, I knowe hée woulde haue gone that voyage, and ſince I had bene in the Sea, I had gone thrée or foure times, becauſe euery yeare once they vſe the ſame order. In that voyage, I tooke with me tenne thouſande female Tonnies, and there were aboue fiue hundreth thouſande female Tonnies which were all big with yoong.</p>
               <p>We hauing taken our leaue of the king, went on our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and in the end entred into the ſtraights of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> and being paſt them, we came vnto <hi>Couil,</hi> and to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>exar,</hi> places vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dominion of the Duke of <hi>Medina Sodinia,</hi> whereas they prepared an armie readie againſt vs, of the which I being aduertiſed, and that there wee were wont to bee hardly dealt withall, willed them to take care of themſelues, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to bee deliuered in that place, it beeing prepared readie for that purpoſe, howe well ſoeuer they looked vnto themſelues I knowe not, but this I am ſure of, that in the ſpace of eight or nine dayes, I wanted aboue fiftie thouſand female Tonnies. Which dammage wee perceiuing, agreed to put our valiaunt Armed Tonnies with them into the key of the Hauen, and while that they were deliuered of their yoong ones, if the Fiſher-men ſought meanes to take them, wee would ſtrike in among the Fiſher-men and their Nets, cutting them aſunder in ſmall péeces, but wée deceiued our ſelues, and founde that our deuice did fall out cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to all our expectations, by reaſon of the great ſtrength and ſkill that the men vſed, whiche is muche greater than that of the Tonnies, and ſo by their mightie force they tooke vs all, with an infinite nomber of the female Tonnies in one Nette, without in a manner receiuing anie damage of vs, but rather great gaines, and as my companions percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues taken, they were diſmayed, and therewith beginning to ſigh, let their armes fall out of their mouthes, whiche I did not, but they tooke mee with my ſworde, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:9880:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
therewith done ſufficient dammage vnto their Nets, and with mée they tooke my faire and ſeconde wife. The Fiſher-men wondring to ſée mée armed in that ſort, ſought to make me forſake my ſworde, whiche I ſtill helde verie faſt, but they pulled ſo long thereat, that in the ende, they pulled an arme and a hande out of my mouth, (wherin I held my ſword,) and then they perceiued in my heade, my forehead, eyes, noſe-thrilles, and the halfe of my mouth. They being much aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at this fighte, helde mee faſt by the arme, and others ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me by the necke, beganne to plucke me out of my fiſhes ſkinne, and as I was halfe out of my caſe, I looked about, and perceiued hard by mee my poore wife <hi>Luna,</hi> in great feare, and rather in more perplexitie then the Fiſher-men, vnto whom I beganne to ſpeake in mans language, and ſayde; Brethren, diſcharge I pray you your conſciences, and let none of you offer to kill mee with the braſſer, for you muſt knowe that I am a man as you are, but make an ende of pulling me out out of my ſkinne, and I will declare great ſecrets vnto you. I ſaide this, becauſe many of my companions laie harde by mee dead, and their heades broken in péeces, with ſtaues whiche the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhermen had for that purpoſe: and then I deſired them of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, that they would let that female Tonny next vnto mee to ſwimme away, becauſe ſhe had bene my companion and wife a great time, and they being greatly aſtoniſhed to ſée and heare me, did as I deſired them. But at ſuch time as my compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on departed from mée, wéeping and in great feare, I ſaide vnto her in my Tonnies language, <hi>Luna</hi> my ſwéete heart, I commit thée to God, I pray thée come no more hither to bee taken, but ſhewe the King and all my friends what thou haſt ſéene, and I pray thée likewiſe to haue a care of thy honour and mine.</p>
               <p>Which done, ſhe without making me any anſwere, ſkip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into the water, and went her way in great feare: vs they tooke from thence, and in my preſence killed my companions, and cut them in péeces at the water ſide, and kept me half a man and half a fiſh in the ſand, with great feare leſt they wold burne me: the fiſhing being ended y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day, they aſked me many queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:9880:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and I told them the truth of euerie thing, praying them to pull me whole out of my fiſhes ſkinne, which as then they did not, but the ſame night they ſet me vpon a Mule, and brought me vnto <hi>Siuil,</hi> preſenting me vnto the moſt noble Duke of <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> great was the admiration that both men and women had to ſée me, for that in long time there had not any thing ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full happened in <hi>Spaine.</hi> In that caſe they held me for the ſpace of eight dayes, during the which time, they vnderſtood of me, what troubles I had paſſed: but at the ende of eight dayes, I felt my ſelfe not well in the part of my bodie that was Fiſhe, and it ſpoyled becauſe it felt not the water, ſo I beſought the Duke and the Duches, that for the loue of God, they woulde cauſe me to be pulled out of that priſon, ſéeing I was brought vnto his grace, ſhewing them what paine I felt, wherunto they agreed, and it was appointed to bee cried throughout all the Towne of <hi>Siuil,</hi> that I ſhould be pulled out of my fiſhes ſkinne, that thereby euerie man might come and ſée my conuerſion, which ſhould bee done vppon a ſcaffold ſet vp in an open market place before his lodging, that all men might beholde it. The Dukes lodging was hard by the Towne of <hi>Siuil,</hi> all the ſtréets entering into the Market place were full, and not ſo much as the toppes of houſes, but were laden with people, ſuch an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſort reſorted thither at that time, then the Duke wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to go, and fetche me out of my Cage wherein they had kept mee euer ſince they brought mee from the ſea ſide, in the way I was muche troubled, becauſe of the great multitude of people, that flocked about me, by which meanes if I had not had Iron grates betwéen me and them, without all doubt they had ſmothered me to death. O good God ſaid I, what alteration is there now in mee? for that I haue ſéene a man in a Cage, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not greatly at his eaſe, but I neuer ſawe a man turned into a fiſh. So they tooke me out and carried me vnto the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place, with fiftie Holberdiers going about me, to kéepe the people from me, and yet could verie hardly do it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:9880:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. How <hi>Lazarus</hi> was openly vpon a ſtage from a Tonny fiſh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in <hi>Siuill,</hi> vnto a man.</head>
               <p>THen I being ſet vpon the ſcaffold, they began to pull mee, ſome by that part of my bodie that was out alreadie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the fiſhes tayle, in ſuch manner, that in the ende they pulled mee out as naked as euer I came foorth of my mothers wombe, and there lay the Tonnie, being nothing but a ſkinne. Then they preſently gaue me a cloak to couer me withall, and the Duke commaunded that a ſute of his apparell ſhould bee brought me, which although they fitted me not, yet I put them on: and then I was ſo feaſted and viſited by the people, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of my continuance there, I had in a manner no time to take my reſt, for that both night and day they ceaſed not to come and ſée me, and to aſke me diuers queſtions, and he that could get but a time to heare me, thought himſelfe happie. But within certaine dayes after my conuerſion, I fell ſicke, becauſe the earth did alter me, being as then not accuſtomed therunto, for that betwéene the nature of the ſea and land there is great difference: ſo that then I began to cleanſe and purge my ſelfe, in ſuch manner, as I thought verely that my troubles and my life would haue ended both together, I pray God deliuer mee from this and other troubles. At the laſt, when I felt my ſelfe ſtrong and able to walke, I tooke my leaue of my frends there, who full ſore againſt their wills granted it vnto me, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deſired to haue had me ſtill there with them, to heare the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous things that had happened vnto me: wherunto I made no conſcience to adde ſomewhat, which they verely beléeued, becauſe they had ſéene me ſo wonderfully conuerted. But in the ende without ſtaying anie longer, they let me goe, and ſent me away verie well prouided for my iourney, and ſo vpon the day before the feaſt of Pentecoſt laſt paſt, I came vnto <hi>Toledo,</hi> the moſt deſirous man in the world to ſée my wife and childe, and imbracing her a thouſand times, which manner of pleaſure I had not had for the ſpace of foure yeares, becauſe it is not vſed in the ſea, for there is nothing elſe but noddes and kiſſes. I came
<pb facs="tcp:9880:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
into the Towne by night, and went ſtraight vnto my houſe, which I found without anie bodie in it: for they were all gone vnto my Maſter the Prieſts houſe, where they were alreadie gone to bed &amp; aſléepe. But I gaue ſo manie blowes at the dore, that therewith they wakened, aſking mee who was there? I telling them, my wife <hi>Eluira</hi> anſwered me verie ſharply with a lowd voyce: Away thou drunkard whatſoeuer thou art, that walkeſt the ſtréetes at this time of the night for to mocke and deceiue poore widowes: comming now at the ende of thrée or foure yeares, (that to my euill fortune God tooke away my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and drowned him in the ſea, in ſight of his maſter, and of manie other that ſaw him ſinke downe) to tell vs a ieſt: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe went to bed againe, without anie more harkening vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me: wherewith I began againe to call &amp; knocke at the dore. Then my Maſter the Prieſt beeing chafed, roſe vp, and came vnto the window, and with a lowd voyce ſaid, what would that fellow haue, what kind of dealing is this? I would faine know who thou art, that in the morning I may reward thée for this thy vncurteous dealing, which at this time of the night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt vnto mens doores that are at reſt, telling them ieſts, and making ſuch a noiſe, that thou breakeſt both their ſléep and their reſt. Signior (ſaid I) let not your worſhip bee offended, and if you deſire ſo much to know who I am, aſmuch doo I deſire to tell it you. I am your Crier <hi>Lazaro de Tormes.</hi> I had ſcarce vttered my words, but I felt a ſtone come buzzing cloaſe by my eares, &amp; that with a good will, and after that two or thrée more: which ſtriking againſt the ſtones in the ſtréete, for that it was paued, made the fier to ſparkle out of them. I perceiuing the danger, and hoping for no better reaſon at his hands for that time, went downe the next ſtréete that lay before mee: and being a good way paſt the houſe, I ſtaied, and he was ſtill in the window, crying out alowd: Come againe to mocke vs, and ſée how thou ſhalt ſpéed. I remembred my ſelfe, and thought to haue turned backe, and once againe to proue the aduenture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was not deſirous to diſcouer my ſelfe vnto anie other. But becauſe it was verie late, I determined to paſſe the reſt of the night there, and in the morning to goe vnto mine owne houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>But it fell out cleane contrarie: for not farre from the place where I ſtood, there was one of the Sheriffes of the Towne, which kept watch about the ſame: who taking my ſword from me, led me vnto priſon. I knew ſome of my Maſters the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieants that were with him, and calling them by their names, I tolde them who I was: but they laughing at me, ſayd, that it was more than thrée yeares paſt that he whom I ſpake of dyed in the Voyage of <hi>Argiel,</hi> and ſo went with mee vnto priſon, where I ſtaied till day light: which being come, when others made them readie and prepared themſelues to goe to Church, and to kéepe ſo holie and Feſtiuall day, I thinking to doo the like, becauſe I ſuppoſed I ſhould bee knowen of them all: in came the Sheriffe that had taken me, and putting a faire paire of fetters on my héeles, and a great chayne about my neck, put me into the houſe where the racke ſtood, ſaying, Let this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman (counterfetting the Iuſtice, and naming himſelfe to be a Crier) ſtay héere theſe few dayes vntill wee may learne who he is, ſéeing you do walke by night to ſcale Prieſts houſes, and to ſéeke after your beſt beloued, when your head is full. Wee came hither in an euill hower ſaid I vnto my ſelfe, and then I ſaid vnto him, that I liued not in anie ſuch ſort, nor yet went abroad to doo anie ſuch things. I cannot tell whether you go or no ſaid he, but euen now I met the Prieſt of Saint <hi>Saludors</hi> Church, comming out of the Sheriffes houſe, ſaying, that the laſt night hee had like to haue béen robbed, and the Théeues thought to haue entered his houſe by force, if he had not defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe with good ſtones: and ſaid that one of the theeues named himſelfe <hi>Lazaro de Tormes</hi> his Crier, and I tolde him that I met you hard by his houſe, and that you ſaid aſmuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and therefore I ſent word that you ſhould be ſafely kept. Then the Iailour ſaid, that Crier which you ſpeake of, was once in this Towne, but he died in the Voyage vnto <hi>Argiel,</hi> I knew him verie well: God be mercifull vnto him, for he was a man ſufficient to carrie two Stopes of wine with the beſt drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker heereabout from one houſe vnto the other, without anie kinde of ſtaggering.</p>
               <p>O vnfortunate wretch that I am ſaid I, which haue not as yet ended al my il fortunes, without doubt they wil begin again to
<pb facs="tcp:9880:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
aſſaile me: what ſhould this meane, that thoſe whom I know, and am preſent in their company, and take them for my frends, ſhould now denie me, and not know me? But it is not poſſible that fortune can croſſe me herein, that my wife ſhould not know me, as being the thing that I moſt deſire, and ſhee mée. With that, I intreated the Kéeper, and gaue him ſomewhat for his paines, that he would goe vnto her, &amp; ſhew her that I am here, and that ſhe would come &amp; fetch me out of priſon. And he laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at me, tooke the royall, ſaying he would doo it: but it ſeemed vnto him that I was not in earneſt, for that if I were hee of whom I ſpake, he ſaid he ſhould know mee, becauſe (ſaid he) I haue ſéene him at the leaſt a thouſand times heere within the priſon, comming to viſite thoſe that had béen whipped: and that hee was the beſt Crier, and had the cléereſt voyce in all <hi>Toledo.</hi> But in the ende (I beeing ſo importunate with him) he did ſo much, that hee brought my Maſter the Prieſt with him: and when I heard him ſpeake in the place where I was, a candle being brought, I had aſmuch ioye, as they in Purgatorie may haue when the time of their deliuerance draweth néere: &amp; wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with gréefe, but more for ioy, I ſaid vnto him: O my good Maſter <hi>Rodrigo de Ieues</hi> chéefe Prieſt of S. <hi>Saluadors,</hi> looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this your good Crier <hi>Lazaro de Tormes,</hi> tormented and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with yrons, hauing for theſe thrée yeares paſſed the moſt ſtraunge and wonderfull aduentures that euer were heard of. Whereat he held the candle ſomewhat nerer vnto my face, and ſaid, <hi>The voyce is <hi>Iacobs,</hi> but the skinne is <hi>Eſaus.</hi>
                  </hi> Brother (ſaid he) it is true that in ſpeach you ſomewhat reſemble him, but in ieſture you are farre different from him that you ſay you are. Then I began to thinke with my ſelfe, and deſired the Iailor to lend me a glaſſe, which he brought me, and when I looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, I perceiued my ſelfe to bee changed in fauour from that I was before, but ſpecially in colour, which I was wont to haue as red as a Pomegranade, I meane as the kernels of the ſame, and now as the yealow of the ſhell, beeing wholly changed in countenaunce, whereat I bleſſed my ſelfe, and ſaid: Now my good Maſter, I doo not meruaile (being thus as I am) that your worſhip nor yet anie of my frends doo not know me, ſéeing that I know not my ſelfe: but worſhip hath made me now to féele it.
<pb facs="tcp:9880:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wherefore Maſter Sheriffe, I would deſire you to giue vs a little libertie to ſpeake together, and you ſhall ſée that I haue not tolde anie lie. He did ſo, and we being alone, I told him all the ſignes and tokens of things paſſed betwéene vs, ſince wee were firſt acquainted, naming the dayes and times. After that I told him all that I had paſſed, and how I was turned into a Tonny, and how long I continued in the ſea, and what I did there, and that it was the water that had ſo changed my colour, and altered my ieſture, which vntill then I had not once looked into: ſo that in the end he ſtood ſtill in a great admiration, and ſaid vnto me. This that you ſay is well knowen here in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be verie true, that there was a man beeing a Tonny fiſh ſéene in <hi>Siuill,</hi> and beſides that the tokens you giue mee are all true, but notwithſtanding I doubt it much to be ſo: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which I will doo for you, ſhalbe to bring my Nurſe hether, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſhee will know you better. Wherewith I gaue him heartie thankes, and beſought him to giue me his hand that I might kiſſe it: and he gaue me his bleſſing, as he had done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times before, but for his hand he refuſed it vnto me. Thus that and thrée dayes more paſſed ouer, and at the ende thereof in the morning the Iuſtices Lieuetenant with his afficers and Clearke came into the priſon to me, and began to examine mée vpon intergatories: which if I would not anſwere vnto, they had commiſſion to ſet me on horſebacke, or to ſay more aptly to hang me vp. Whereat I could not chuſe but ſhed manie teares, fetching moſt great ſighes, and complaining vnto my ſelf of my great miſfortune that followed me continually: and with the greateſt and beſt reaſons I could deuiſe, I beſought the Lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant that as then he would not torment me, becauſe I was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſufficiently vexed and gréeued, which to prooue, I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to come néere and behold my ieſture: whereat bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the light ſomewhat néerer hee ſaid, Certainly I know not what force may doo in manie things, but as farre as I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hee is not without great gréefe, which by his diſpoſition may well be ſéene: let vs leaue him at this time, vntill hee bee ſomewhat better, or elſe that he dieth, and quit himſelfe of all, and ſo they left me. Then againe I beſought the Kéeper, that he would goe vnto my Maſters houſe, and intreate him on my
<pb facs="tcp:9880:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
behalfe to accompliſh his word and promiſe giuen vnto me, that hee would bring my wife with him vnto the priſon: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall I gaue him another royall, (becauſe they neuer walke in vaine). Thether he went, and returned me anſwere, that the next day they both promiſed me to come: wherewith I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat comforted, that night I ſlept better than at other times. And in my dreame me thought I ſaw my Ladie &amp; frend the Truth, who ſhewed her ſelfe verie angrie toward mee and ſaid: Thou <hi>Lazarus</hi> dooſt not ſéeke to amend thy life, whereas thou didſt promiſe me (being in the Sea) not to let mee depart from thée, and now ſince thou cameſt forth, thou haſt in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner neuer once looked vpon me: for which cauſe, the diuine Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice hath thought it good to puniſh thée in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thine owne Countrie and in thine houſe thou ſhouldeſt not be knowen, but ſhouldſt be put vnto the racke, as an euill dooer. In the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thy wife will come, and thou ſhalt bee deliuered with thy honor and credit. And ſo ſhe departed, leauing me verie ioyfull of ſuch a viſion, knowing ſhe ſaid moſt true, and that my puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was moſt iuſt, becauſe the lyes which I tolde and mixed with my ſpeach were ſo manie and ſo great, although thoſe that were true, were verie ſtrange and wonderfull of themſelues, that they were ſufficient with the verie fear in hearing of them to ſtrike men dead: which fault I determined to repent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and for the ſame was verie ſorrowfull. Morning being come, my ieſture and countenance became as it was at the firſt, and then I was knowen both of my Maſter and my wife, and ſo taken out of priſon and brought home to my houſe, where I found my daughter almoſt big inough to make another. And after I had reſted my ſelfe for a time, I returned againe vnto my pot and my cup, whereby in ſhort ſpace after I had my own proper ieſture, and a pleaſant good life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:9880:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. How <hi>Lazarus</hi> went vnto <hi>Salamanca,</hi> and of the frendſhip hee found there, and of the diſputation he held with the Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and how he dealt with the Students of the Vniuerſitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Liuing ſomewhat at my pleaſure, and being verie well vſed and apparelled, had a deſire to trauell from thence to ſée the Countrey of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and to ſport and ſolace my ſelfe for a time, becauſe I was in a manner filled with the ſhadow of the ſea. And thinking with my ſelfe whether I ſhould goe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at the laſt I went vnto <hi>Salamanca,</hi> where it is ſaid the ſeuen Sciences haue their dwelling place: and it was thus, that I had manie times wiſhed and deſired to proue if I could deceaue anie one of thoſe Abbots or long gowned fellowes, which call themſelues Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates. And as the towne is full of them, ſo the ſmell and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of them ſtretcheth farre and néere, although I pray God kéepe them from my houſe in the night time. I went therefore preſently vnto that towne: and thinking vpon the ſea; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I had béen, I meruailed with my ſelfe to beholo that I ſaw in the towne, which was ſomewhat more than I had heard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of it, whereof I will tell you, ſpecially of one thing that happened vnto me therein. I going along in one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtréets, met a man riding vpon an aſſe, (and becauſe as then I was ſomewhat ſmall eyed and wearie, I could not goe anie further, nor yet turne backward without great paine) the man began to crie out and ſay, Out of the way Signior Batchelor. I ſtird not, but giuing him a more honorable name, cride, Out of the way Signior <hi>Licenciado,</hi> out of the way in the diuells name: and therewith began to lay vpon him with a ſtaffe that I bare in my hand. Whereat you might preſently haue ſéene him kicke forwards and backwards: ſo that what with maſter <hi>Licenciado</hi> on one ſide, and the <hi>Cauallero</hi> on the other, I neuer in my life ſaw better ſport, nor a <hi>Licenciado</hi> of his qualitie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom all men gaue place, or that had ſo manie people to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him. But then I knew him preſently to bee one that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe to be honoured with great names, as I had done in the ſea, becauſe of my force and valor, among the Tonnyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Yet neuertheleſſe they did honor to others as well as vnto me, for although they called me Signior, yet they gaue me no more libertie therby, than I got vnto my ſelfe by force, among them. So that I aſſure your worſhip, if I ſhould continue long there, I would rather be the Aſſe-headed <hi>Licencioado,</hi> then poore <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarillo de Tormes.</hi> From thence, being among the preaſe, I went into a Colledge, where I ſawe ſo many Students, and heard ſo many voyces, that I dare ſay there was not one among them but was more wearied with crying, than with wit. And among many of others that I knew (although not one of them knewe me) as God would I founde one of my friends of <hi>Toledo,</hi> with whom I had bin acquainted, and he ſerued with two mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which were of the beſt in the Colledge. He being a wiſe fellow, and waiting on them in their chamber, told his maſters of me, in ſuch maner, that it was worth a dinner and ſomewhat more vnto me. True it is, it was after the maner of Colledges, a ſhort dinner, and litle meate, ill dreſſed and worſe ſerued: for I aſſure you, there was neuer a bone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eſcaped without brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſucking. In dinner time we talked of many things, and I replied again ſo wel, that they both perceiued I had gone further for my experience, than they had done for their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: then I told them what had happened vnto <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and that with ſuch words, that they all aſked me, where I had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, whether in <hi>France, Flanders,</hi> or in <hi>Italie,</hi> and if at that time it had pleaſed God to haue granted me but a word or two of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, I had poſed them all, but at the laſt I left off ſpeaking, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not deſirous to giue them occaſion to aſke me any more, leſt they might propounde ſomething whereunto I could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Neuertheleſſe they thinking me to be an other maner of man than I was, determined to haue me openly defend cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine concluſions, and I becauſe I knewe them all to bee Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilians, as I my ſelfe am, ſo that without ſhame I might ſhewe my ſelfe before them all, refuſed not, for hee that knowes howe to behaue himſelfe among the Tonnies, which plaie but with their ſnoutes, will make his partie good inough with them that plaie but with their tongues: The time was appointed to be the next day following, and all the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie were charged to bee there without faile, for to heare vs,
<pb facs="tcp:9880:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
where your worſhip might haue ſéene your <hi>Lazarus</hi> in greateſt honour in the Cittie, ſet among ſo many Doctors, Licentialls, and Batchellers, that I aſſure you, the tenth part of them were ſufficient to till all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fields in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and with the tithes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to ſatiſfie the whole world: there you might behold ſo many colours of apparel, and ſo many degrées in the ſeates, that there was no account made of a man, but of his degrée. And before I went in among them, they woulde haue had me apparelled as they were, which <hi>Lazarus</hi> refuſed, becauſe that ſéeing I was a ſtranger, and not any ſtudent of that vniuerſitie, they ought not to wonder at the ſame, but rather to iudge by the learning, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the diſputation was to that ende) then by the apparell, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were vnaccuſtomed. I ſaw them all in ſuch order and ſo graue, to ſay the truth, whoſoeuer ſhould ſay I had more feare than ſhame, or rather more ſhame than feare, ſhould not mocke me. But to come to the matter, <hi>Lazarus</hi> being ſet in his place, (beholde what a ſtudent I was) euerie one ſéeing my Doctorall preſence, and howe grauely I could behaue my ſelfe, and in as good order as they, the Rector deſired to be the firſt that might diſpute with me, althogh it were not the cuſtom among them. And ſo he propounded a queſtion ſomewhat hard and difficult to be anſwered: aſking me howe many Tunnes of water are in the ſea, whereunto (I being a man well ſtudied, and it not being long ſince my comming from thence,) knew verie well how to anſwere: ſaying, hee ſhould cauſe all the waters to bee ſtaid and kept in one place: which done, I would quickly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it, and then ſatiſfie his demaund. He hearing my ſhort and readie anſwere, ſuch as the beſt of them all could not haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and being at a ſtaie, for that he thought to haue poſed mée, finding it to bee impoſſible with that queſtion to doo it, left that charge vnto me to meaſure it, and then to tell him. The Rector being abaſhed with that anſwere, put an other argument vnto me, thinking to trie my wit, to ſée if I would make him as pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie an anſwere to the ſecond, as I did vnto the firſt: he aſked me how many dayes had paſſed from the creation of <hi>Adam,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til that time: as though I had bin alwaies liuing in the world, with a penne in my hand kéeping account of them, when as to tel you the truth, I do not remember mine owne, but only that
<pb facs="tcp:9880:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I was once a prieſtes boye, and then a ſchoolemaiſters boye, and ſuch like, wherof I kept better account than of my dayes. But this notwithſtanding I aunſwered him, ſaying there was no more then ſeuen, becauſe that when thoſe ſeuen are paſt, there followeth other ſeuen, and ſo it had continued from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world vntil that time, and ſhould likewiſe continue ſo to the end of the world: then your worſhip might haue ſéene <hi>Lazaro</hi> eſtéemed a great Doctor, among the Doctors, and a wiſe maiſter of art among the Licentiates. Now the third queſtion was for to win the victory, and becauſe I had waded ſo well out of two of them, the Rector thought that in the third I would be graueled. Wherefore he willed me to ſatiſfie him in the third queſtion: whereat I anſwered him very readily, that I would do ſo, and that not only to his third, but to as many as he would propounde betwéene that and the next day. Then he aſked me, where the ende of the world is? What Philoſophers are theſe ſaide I vnto my ſelfe? for ſéeing that I neuer went about the whole world, how can I anſwere him? But if he had aſked mée the ende of the water, I could haue anſwered him ſomewhat better. Yet I anſwered vnto his queſtion, and ſaid it to be in the ſame place, wherein we then were, and if he meaſured it hée ſhould certainly finde it to be ſo, offering if it were not true, that they ſhould eſtéeme and account me vnworthie to enter into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Colledge, he perceiuing himſelfe ſhamde by my anſweres, and that ſtill thinking to giue a good checke, he receiued an ill mate, put me the fourth queſtion very boldly, aſking me howe far the earth is from heauen. Your worſhip might then haue ſéene me hake and ſpit, thinking how to anſwere, for I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at a <hi>non plus,</hi> becauſe hee knewe verie well, that I neuer went any ſuch way, if he had aſked me what manner of life the Tonnies vſe, and what language they ſpeake, I could haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen better reaſon for it, yet I was not therewith altogither grounded, but anſwered him, that heauen is verie neare vnto the earth, for that the ſongs that men ſing here vpon earth, are heard vp into heauen, howe ſoughtly ſoeuer men ſing or ſpeake, which if he would not beléeue, I had him go vp into heauen, and I would ſing here below verie ſoughtly, and if he did not heare it, he ſhould condemne me for a foole. I aſſure your worſhip, that
<pb facs="tcp:9880:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
at the ſame anſwer you might haue ſéene the Rector at ſuch an exigent, that ceaſing to propound anie more queſtions, he left off, referring the reſt vnto others: but when they ſaw him thus foyled, there was not one of them that durſt begin, but all lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their places, ſaid and affirmed my anſweres to be moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent. Whereat I neuer ſaw my ſelfe to be ſo much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red among men, nor ſo much Signiored heere, and Signiored there, ſo that <hi>Lazarus</hi> his honour increaſed daily: which was partly the more, becauſe of the apparell the good Duke gaue me, for if it had not béen for them, thoſe long gowned fellowes would haue made no more account of mee, than I did of the Tonnyes in the ſea, although I diſſembled. But then they all came vnto me, ſome commending me for my prompt and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie anſweres, and others being glad to ſée and heare me ſpeake. Whereby (this my great abilitie being ſéene) the name of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> was in euerie mans mouth, and I walked through the Citie with more buzzing and noiſe, than I did among the Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes. My hoſtes bad mee to ſupher with them, and I was as willing to goe, although I ſéemed to refuſe them at the firſt, making as though I were bidden by others: and to conclude we ſupt, I néed not tell you with what, becauſe it was a Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates ſupper, after their manner, although I perceiued verie well that the ſupper was prepared by changing of bookes, and yet it was good inough. After we had ſupt, and the cloath taken away, there was a paire of cardes laid on the boord for a colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was a daily cuſtome, and ſurely I was better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them, than in the diſputations of the Rector. At the laſt monie began to be laid vpon the boord, which I deſired to ſée: and they as being verie nimble in that arte, knew how to vſe a thouſand ſhifts and flights to compaſſe mee in, I had almoſt loſt all my money, for that for a while it went but croſſely with me, but at the laſt I handled the matter ſo well, that they payd for all, and for the ſupper likewiſe, and I put fiftie royalls of plate in my purſe that I got among them. I would wiſh ye to beware of him that hath bin a ſignior among the Tonnies. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after they would take héed of <hi>Lazaro,</hi> and I to diſpatch my ſelfe away, prayed them to ſpeake ſomewhat vnto me in Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes language: if not they could not vnderſtand me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9880:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>But after that, fearing leaſt they ſhould offer me any iniurie, and becauſe no occaſion might bee had, I departed from them, thinking that I could not alwayes haue good fortune at playe. So I determined to returne home againe, making my ſelf me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with the fiftie ryals I had gotten, and ſomewhat more with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, which for their credits I will not preſently rehearſe: and comming to my houſe, I founde all well there, only that there wanted money. Then I called to minde the Dollors that lye hidden in the ſea, and therewith I began to be ſad, and thought with my ſelfe, that if I might ſpéede as well as I did in <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manca,</hi> I woulde ſet vp a ſchoole in <hi>Toledo,</hi> and though it were onely to teach the Tonnies language which I thinke no man but would deſire to ſtudie it. But thinking better vppon the matter, I ſaw there was nothing to be gotten, becauſe it would bee no profite to any man, wherewith I left off my deuiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I could haue bene well content to haue had the fame, to be the founder of a Vniuerſitie in ſo noble a Cittie, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenter of a new language neuer knowne before among men. Hitherto I haue ſhewed you the courſe of my life, ſince the voyage of <hi>Argel,</hi> what more ſhall happen, as time ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, your worſhip ſhalbe certified thereof. In the meane time, I reſt wholly at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement and ſeruice.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours, <hi>Lazaro de Tormes</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9880:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
